<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Christian looking-glasse or, A glimps of Christs unchangably everlasting love. Discovered in several sermons, in the parish-church of Sutton-Valence. Kanc. By Hezekiah Holland anglo-hibernus, minister of the gospel at Sutton de Valentiâ.</title>
            <author>Holland, Hezekiah, fl. 1638-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 175 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2425</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1376_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209245</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868131</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868131</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169877</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86456)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169877)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 180:E1376[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Christian looking-glasse or, A glimps of Christs unchangably everlasting love. Discovered in several sermons, in the parish-church of Sutton-Valence. Kanc. By Hezekiah Holland anglo-hibernus, minister of the gospel at Sutton de Valentiâ.</title>
                  <author>Holland, Hezekiah, fl. 1638-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8, [4], 9-125, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. &amp; E.M. for George Calvert, at the Half-moon in Watling-street, neer Pauls stump,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Text continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A Christian looking-glasse, or A glimps of Christs love.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sep: 4th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169877:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Chriſtian LOOKING-GLASSE: OR, A glimps of Chriſts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changably everlaſting love.</p>
            <p>Diſcovered in ſeveral SERMONS, In the Pariſh-Church of <hi>Sutton-Valence.</hi> Kanc.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Hezekiah Holland</hi> Anglo-Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernus, Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Sutton</hi> de <hi>Valentiâ.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Deus ſum &amp; non mutor.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mal. 3.6</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <bibl>1 John 4 8.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>I have loved thee with an everlaſting love.</p>
               <bibl>Jerem. 31.3.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <bibl>John 13.1.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T.R.</hi> &amp; <hi>E.M.</hi> for <hi>George Calvert,</hi> at the <hi>Half-moon</hi> in <hi>Watling-ſtreet,</hi> neer <hi>Pauls</hi> ſtump. 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:169877:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:169877:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFUL The <hi>Deputy Lieutenants</hi> of the County of KENT.</head>
            <head type="sub">In particular, to the Right Worſhipful <hi>Richard Beal</hi> and <hi>Lambert Godfrey</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S all Rivers pay tribute to the Ocean from whence they receive their water, ſo I (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring my (many wayes) engagements to the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Commons of <hi>England</hi> (for countenance and maintenance) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſtranger (a kind of a baniſhed man) out of <hi>Ireland</hi> (knowing ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude to be the worſt badge of a Chriſtian) have been bold to preſent yee with theſe lines; Worthy and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169877:3"/>Worſhipful Gentlemen, Yee who are a repreſentative of the Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Houſe of Commons in this County. Yee uſually receive their debts for them <hi>Here,</hi>—and give them a juſt account; Be pleaſed to accept of this mite; which, though no way anſwerable to my engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to them, yet who payes leaſt, is more out of debt then he that payes nothing at all. Pardon me Gentlemen, if ſince I had occaſion to make my thoughts legible, I have coveted your Worſhips to ſhrine them (being worthy to be Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to greater offenders:) In theſe lines yee may in parr ſee how I ſpend my Lords Dayes—in <hi>Sutton;</hi> in which if any word have but the face of an enemy againſt <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State</hi> (though every Miniſter cannot be at preſent ſatisfied with every conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in them) remember they are the words of a quiet man, in whom ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was found any true ground of <hi>jealouſie</hi> or <hi>feare</hi> of <hi>diſaffection,</hi> no
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169877:3"/>not when the grand riſing in <hi>Kent</hi> was carried on even with a generall applauſe; when (pardon my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) ſome of your ſelves began to play with the bait, I never ſmelt at it, ſcarce ſwam in the River, though I had more reaſon then ſome others to wiſh his Majeſty well, being a Penſioner of his in the Iriſh-univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie many years.</p>
            <p>And truly 'tis beleeved, that the often riſing of thoſe who only Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten themſelves by the name of his Majeſties friends, were the occaſion of his ſudden death. By the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding lines you know my Countrey to be <hi>Ireland,</hi> a Countrey like <hi>Joves,</hi> where no creature is poyſonous (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you object that much experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhewes poyſon to be lodg'd in the heart of the Natives;) Truly Gentlemen, I underſtand not the myſtery of that Rebellion; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance the Spaniſh King had factors there; ſurely if a Crowne were the the prize of the game, 'twere no
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169877:4"/>wonder to ſee foule play among the gameſters: Yet my thinks if the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh did not bear ſome good will to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Engliſh, we might have had worſe carding of late when they had almoſt the whole game in their hands; doubtleſſe tyrants ſinnes call for bloud; their bodies ſeldome have any other enbalming; forbearance is no acquittance. I fear me ſhould they pay the old debt eaſily, they would be apt to run (too ſoon) upon our ſcore again.</p>
            <p>And I pray God, the life given to it by the late peace, be not as life given by ſome Phyſitian to a woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded man, only for ſome few groans the longer.</p>
            <p>In fine, the chief cauſe of our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery there, was our ſin, <hi>de te deſtructio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tua</hi> —it runne over, which made God fill up his Viols to the brim; how ſugared ſoever it was, God has juſtly ſoured it for her Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; but I take my leave of that Kingdom for the preſent; the Lord
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169877:4"/>look upon them, and bleſſe the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces he has intended for them.</p>
            <p>Five years ago I came out of that Kingdom into this; how ſorry was I to ſee Engliſh men the ſubject of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh mens valour? as if yee had ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned any ſhould conquer ye but your ſelves,
<q>Vt nemo Ajacem poſſit ſuperare niſi Ajax.</q>
When your Supernumeraries were ſpent, my thought I ſaw ye ſpend of the main ſtock, half of which would have reſtored <hi>Ireland</hi> and to ſpare.</p>
            <p>But that troubled me much (as a Miniſter) to ſee ſuch diſſentions in Religion. I am afraid of Hereticks, who ſeem to confute God &amp; truth, but as their parents, at laſt they will befoole themſelves: the ſnuffing of a light ſeldom puts it out, but makes it burn the brighter. Yee have here unparalleld Miniſters, tis true; but Hereticks are miracle-proof, words in them make little impreſſion.</p>
            <p>Errours of ſmaller bulk (till God
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169877:5"/>ſhall reveal) may be better tolerated. <hi>Sed haec libertas in vitium ruat.</hi> A green errour (if no care taken) may feſter to an old ſoar of Hereſie. But being a ſtranger I forbear; pardon me Gentlemen, I have been bold as a traveller to give you ſome account of my travels. He that made yee, ſave yee: The Lord bleſſe yee all from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſheba.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridge-houſe in</hi> Sutton-Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence <date>
                     <hi>Iuly</hi> 10. 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>So prayes your moſt humble ſervant,</hi> HEZEK-HOLLAND. Anglo-Hib.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:169877:5"/>
            <head>To the truly vertuous and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Gentlewoman M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi> HELLEN TOMSON, <hi>Alias WOODGREEN:</hi> Increaſe of Grace and Eternall Glory.</head>
            <p>WHen I conſidered your conſtant reading Meditations, Prayers, Chriſtian charity, tears, your much ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtring your ſelf from the world: when <hi>I</hi> looked upon your deare Siſter <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> whoſe practice is Chriſt, whoſe ſtudy is Divinity, whoſe whole work is Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; My thought your religious courſes invited as well as deſerved my pains; (much endeared Aunts,) indeed I have not with a little joy taken notice, how oft by me (when have been accidental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at your houſe,) you have ſent your cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to the door, not knowing to whom, ('twas enough they were poor People,)
<pb facs="tcp:169877:6"/>not deſiring your left hand ſhould know what your right hand did; alſo how oft you have chid with your ſervants for cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the poor, beggars (in contempt,) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe perchance we are all ſuch; We all ſay, <hi>Give us this day our daily bread</hi>—Alſo ſince the ſame hand which made them ſuch can lay our honour in the duſt. Indeed the time ſpent in Gods ſervice is the moſt choice time, the only days of comfort, for is not one houre ſpent with Chriſt, more precious, joyous, comfortable, then all the reſt of our days? how do theſe end in mirth, thoſe in mourning?</p>
            <p>I wonder not to heare <hi>Moſes</hi> from a Courtier to become a fellow-ſufferer with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſince his recompence as well here as hereafter was ſo great. He left a tyrant King for a mercifull God, a Court of pleaſure, for a Kingdome of grace, At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants for Angels, Courtiers for Saints, Dainties for Graces, a kind of Sonſhip for true Adoption, a Kingdome of Trouble for a Heaven of Ioy.</p>
            <p>How inſipid are things below to a Chriſtian in reſpect of Chriſt? how like the white of an egge (in <hi>Job</hi>) without taſt? how empty is the Creature, to the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator;
<pb facs="tcp:169877:6"/>what delight is there in the Word? what heavenly conference among Saints? what humble familiarity have they with Chriſt by Prayer? how doth he anſwer them, filling their hearts with as it were laughter, and their ſouls with joy? they envy not the worlds favourites or dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, while they enjoy their Chriſt. How ſad is a Chriſtian that (but ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for a time) hath loſt his Chriſt? (who is his life and ſoule of his ſoule) what faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is in that ſoule? what enquiry after Chriſt by Prayer, as the Spouſe in the Canticles doth.</p>
            <p>What hungring and thirſting is in the Saints after Chriſt? (more then in the Hart after the water-brooks)</p>
            <p>How dejected is a Saint after ſinning? what a Stranger to himſelf? how mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully he walks? how unpleaſing is every thing to him? what rivers of tears doth he ſhed? what ſorrow like his, till recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to his God?</p>
            <p>How do the Saints hate ſin (tho they fall into it,) how do they condemne, ſtrive to crucifie it, (tho it dog them?) fleſh and blood never taught them this, nor the Divel will not willingly caſt out himſelf,
<pb facs="tcp:169877:7"/>you may ſee whoſe children they are, by their practice and obedience.</p>
            <p>How eaſily do they kiſſe the rod when their Father ſcourgeth them? how like <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> are they content to part with all to enjoy their <hi>David?</hi> how do they live by Promiſe, counting it far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond an inheritance? how eaſily do they ſubmit their will to Gods Will? in ſumme, how are they delighted in goodneſſe? how much in the Company of Saints? (to ſee Chriſt in them, to ſee them deckt with his graces,) more then in the company of Princes that have not acquaintance with Chriſt? Dear Aunt, I love your practice, and ſtrive to imitate, ſince it will bring e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall peace. Pardon me if I have a little commented upon your (I hope, a Saints actions) I will do no more, <hi>I</hi> could do no leſſe; Go on to Perfection, to them that overcome Chriſt will give Crowns—</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Sutton-Valence</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>July</hi> 10. 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Which that you may do— and obtain, ſhall be the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant prayers &amp; endeavours of your loving friend and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged kinſman.</hi> H. Holland.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:169877:7"/>
            <head>To the <hi>Courteous</hi> READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have been very juſt in publiſhing theſe Heads of Sermons (as delivered,) Time might have made me Parent of ſome more worthy piece on this Subject, but whiles I was delivered of this, ſome as it were preſent at the labour, (but not of my ſaid Pariſh) accuſed it of Baſtardy, not being from the true ſeed, the word; which made me own in publick this weak exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe: now the world may ſee I dare publiſh what I preach.</p>
            <p>I ſometimes ſeem to diminiſh ſin in the Saints; <hi>John</hi> ſayes, <hi>they ſin not;</hi> I mean but as he does, they do not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> make a trade of ſin, they do <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ex</hi> Iohn <hi>3.</hi> ſin, in ſome acts, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit; they do <hi>peccare,</hi> not <hi>dare operam pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cato</hi> (as <hi>Beza</hi> tranſlates the words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>&amp;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) ſin, not walk, (implying an habit) in the way of ſin—they ſin with much reluctancy, not with a full ſwing, they hate what they do.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:169877:8"/>
            <p>They run not after errors, but are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertaken, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ex Gal. 6.1.</hi> they fully cloſe not with ſuch: Chriſt hath told <hi>John, Rev. 13.8.</hi> thoſe that worſhip the Beaſt have not their names written in heaven: but they whoſe names are written in heaven, eſcape the beaſt, and all falſe teachers from hurting them much.</p>
            <p>The name of the Beaſt is <hi>666.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Pope aſcribes this name to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; <hi>VICarIUS GeneraLIs DeI In ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rIs;</hi> where the numerall letters make up the ſaid number by which you know the Beaſt.</p>
            <p>I have uſed many moderne Authors, which fitted my purpoſe, and many digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, (as my manner of preaching is) <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredi patimur non divagari;</hi> what faults you find, ſuppoſe them <hi>errata.</hi> So farewell. Yours to uſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Anglo-Hibernus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermons">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:169877:8"/>
            <head>A Chriſtian LOOKING-GLASSE: OR, A glimps of Chriſts unchang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably Everlaſting Love; Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in ſeveral <hi>Sermons</hi> in the Pariſh Church of <hi>Sutton-Valence.</hi> Kanc. by <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glo-hibernus.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOHN 13. verſe 1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Having loved his own which were in the world, he loved them to the end.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ee, ſee thou (unhappily) wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Arminius,</hi> Chriſt has a people whom he cals his own in the world, diſtinct from the world, not all the world. A world of Believers in the world. A people he chooſes in the midſt of a people, a Nation out of a Nation. <hi>Peter</hi> cals the Saints <hi>a peculiaer people;</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:169877:9"/>our Saviour his <hi>a little flock,</hi> diſtiguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the large drove of the world. Chriſt has a Church in <hi>Rome,</hi> not all the Romans. A Church at <hi>Corinth,</hi> not all the Corinthians. A Church at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> not all the <hi>Epheſians.</hi> And though <hi>Paul</hi> by way of charity in every Epiſtle in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral call's them Saints, yet in a peculiar manner aimes at the people of Chriſt, every one of which either was a Saint, or look't much like one; true, all the world is owned by God, he created all, and all's provided for by him; <hi>Dives</hi> is the ſon of creation and common provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. <hi>Son, remember thou in thy life time receivedſt thy good things,</hi> Luke 16. v. 25. Theſe are but entertained in the common out-Court; but his own by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption in the inner roomes of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and care.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His owne?</hi> how came he by them? God gave them to him, even while yet ſlaves to Satan; he was (as we ſay) to win them and wear them; he redeemed them, they gave up their ſelves to him in Baptiſme, he married them, cloathed them, entred into a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with them, and they became his, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. v. 8.—God has a ſet number of his own, <hi>I heard the number of them
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169877:9"/>that were ſealed</hi> (ſaies <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 4. though there is a certain number for an uncertain, to which none can be added, from w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> none can be taken; they then who as the Diſciples have their names written in heaven, are happy and may rejoyce—Since we are thine O Saviour, poſſeſſe thy ſelfe of that heart wherein none can claime an intereſt but thy ſelf. Let us not, O let us not proſtitute our ſelves to the love of the world. Come O Saviour to thine own, make thine own receive thee, rejoyce in thee.</p>
            <p>Chriſt certainly has not redeemed all; for then having ſatisfied offended juſtice, what ſhould hinder their ſalvation? Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication? <hi>He that ſo freely gave his Son, how ſhall he not freely give us all things,</hi> even Application?—You'l ſay, all fell, therefore Chriſt muſt redeem all; nay, rather as all fell, ſo all by Chriſt ſhall be quickened in the reſurrection. Chriſt payed indeed a ſufficient price for the world, but not efficient: he redeemed the elect only; now all are not<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, poſiti: non diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiti. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> hoc eſt diem ipſi conſtituebant, ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, deſignabant. <hi>actor. ult. v.</hi> 23. Noman is natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſed towards Chriſt. <hi>We are not able of our ſelves to think one good thought.</hi> Away <hi>Arminius,</hi> God ſaw no good in us when he elected us, we were in our blood when he ſaid, <hi>live. Elegit nos &amp; fecit fideles,</hi> I obtained mercy to be faithfull, ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es the Apoſtle. The Hebrew Doctors ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what agree with <hi>Arminius,</hi> and would have a man diſpoſed to good before the ſpirit of prophecy light on him; but the ſpirit found <hi>Saul</hi> nought, and <hi>Balaam</hi> mingled with malice and covetouſneſſe; <hi>Eliſha</hi> was not compoſed in mind (tho ſanctified) when to prophecy, and cals for a Minſtrell to diſpell griefe for <hi>Eliſha's</hi> death. <hi>Aquinas</hi> affirmes <hi>diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem non requiri ne ad prophetiam</hi> (whether God reveale himſelfe by Viſion, Dream, or the more noble way, as he did to Chriſt by word) <hi>Spiritus replet paſtorum Armentari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um— &amp; Prophetam facit.</hi> Yet when the ſpirit of prophecie lighted on one undiſpoſed to good, as <hi>Balaam</hi> or <hi>Saul,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if in a Viſion or Dream, they might be abſtracted from theſe vices during the prohpecie and time of illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation the ſoule being in a trance oft, and ſo moſt fixed on the object.</note> ordained
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169877:10"/>or elected to life, for then all would have been prayed for, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17. <hi>v.</hi> 9. and all would beleeve, <hi>for as many as were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to eternal life beleeved</hi> Acts 13.48. But we ſee few beleeve and perſevere to the end; yet all Chriſt's do and ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve; increaſe of them is dayly ſeen; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very loſt groat ſhall be found; nothing can hinder, they (when built) are built upon a ſure foundation, <hi>Chriſt the Rock; the gates of hell,</hi> that is, hells ſtrength and policy ſhall not prevaile againſt them. <hi>No weapon formed againſt them ſhall proſper,</hi> Eſa. 54. <hi>ver. ult. Chriſt's the builder,</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> the meanes which cannot faile. If God ſend his <hi>Word,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:169877:10"/>great ſhall be the company of them that Praiſe him, even in this ſenſe—the building as it ſhall go forward, ſo it will laſt, ſince the foundation Chriſt cannot ſhrink. Chriſt aſſures us his blood was ſhed (not for all) <hi>but for many for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes;</hi> thoſe he loves, thoſe he will continue <hi>to love to the end,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the text, <hi>whom he loves, he loves unto the end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the former part of this chapt. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the love and lowlineſſe of Chriſt: his love, in ſo willingly departing out of this world for us, <hi>ver.</hi> 1. his lowlineſſe in waſhing his Diſciples feet, <hi>ver.</hi> 5.— that the Head and Maſter Chriſt ſhould ſtoop to the feet of his ſervants, and waſh and wipe them, is an unparalleld example of humility.</p>
            <p>The firſt verſe ſpeaks him God and man; God, in that he knew his houre of departing out of this world; for as God he knew all things, though as man he was ignorant of many; about the time of the ſacrificing the Paſſeover, Chriſt our Paſteover was ſacrificed for us. Man, in that, by death depart he muſt, for the God-head could not ſuffer; this one text evinceth what ever Jewes Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, Hereticks or heathens may falſely
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169877:11"/>conceive of Chriſt, Intimations and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of his Divinity run as parallel with thoſe of his Humanity almoſt throughout the Hiſtories in the Goſpel concerning him.</p>
            <p>His birth ſpake him a man; but to be borne of a Virgin (and as ſome conceive without<note n="*" place="margin">The pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment <hi>(in ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſhalt thou bring forth)</hi> was to the woman, not the child; So Chriſts being without ſin ordinarily excuſes not the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> who had ſin; and a Redeemer or Saviour, <hi>My ſoule has rejoyced in God my Saviour.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Athanaſ. de ſententiis Dionyſii.</hi>
               </note> paine) together with a ſtrange Starre, and quire of Angels, proclaimed him God.</p>
            <p>His ſwadling bands and the Manger ſpake him man, one diſreſpected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men; but the Shepheards and Wiſe men worſhipping him, expreſſed him God. His Baptiſme adminiſtred by <hi>Iohn,</hi> declared him man; but the voice from Heaven to be God. Tempted in the Wilderneſſe, man; overcame as God. Wept for <hi>Lazerus,</hi> man; raiſed him from
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169877:11"/>the dead, God; ſtept on the ſeas, man; but after he was awaked, ſtilled the waves, God; tempered the clay with ſpittle, man; but opened the eyes of one borne blind, God. Laſtly, by his death ſhewed himſelf man; by his powerful and moſt (to us) comfortable reſurrection, God.</p>
            <p>Each ſentence ſhewes his lowlineſſe, in that he was made man, and his love in that lowlineſſe, <hi>who being in the forme of God, thought it no robbery to be equall with God, but made himſelf of no reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; took upon him the form of a ſervant, he humbled himſelf and became obedient, even to death, even the death of the Croſſe,</hi> Phil. 2. v. 6 7, 8. <hi>Supplicii genus crude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſſimum, deterrimumque, inquit</hi> Cicero. The conſtancy of that love is expreſſed in the words, <hi>he loves unto the end;</hi> the earneſtneſſe and integrity of it is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable in the word there uſed to love, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting in the original, to love with the heart and mind by adhering to the thing loved with content and ſatisfaction; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>magis eſt quam</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ut Amo apud Latinos magis eſt quamdiligo, Me aut amabis, aut quo contentus ſim, diliges.</hi> Cicero. As Chriſt thus loves his owne, ſo ought they to love him; <hi>Thou ſhalt love</hi> (the ſame words) <hi>the Lord thy God
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169877:12"/>with all thy heart</hi> — Matth. 22.37.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> vel ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem vel ad ſeculum, vel perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem ſignificat.</note> The conſtancy and perpetuity of Chriſts love may be noted from the word in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal, ſignifying the end; it may be rendred by perfection, <hi>till we become perfect men in Chriſt,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Epheſ. 4 13, He loves us; he loves here to the end of dayes, and for ever hereafter.</p>
            <p>Hence obſerve theſe concluſions, God through Chriſt loves his own; Then, or ſecondly, he loves them for ever— The truth of this concluſion will appeare in the enſuing diſcourſe. Why God loved loſt man, not the Angels (being more excellent creatures) man in whom was nothing but deformity; no other reaſon can be rendred <hi>à priori,</hi> but his own will and pleaſure, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, foreſeeing the death of Chriſt as the meanes both of love and election (though not the cauſe of either, redemption being the effect of Gods love in the general) he loves man now becauſe redeemed by the death of Chriſt, juſtified by his blood, adopted to be conformable to his image; ſanctified in part by his Spirit, becauſe the member of Chriſt, the temple of the holy Spirit, the Spouſe of Chriſt, and ſubject of him the King of Saints, <hi>Revel.</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> 3. God loves his people firſt, and gives Chriſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169877:12"/>for them, then love them becauſe they are Chriſts, and partakers of his graces.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Concluſion, God loves unchangably and everlaſtingly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is ſet down, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>I have loved thee with an everlaſting love.</hi> God being love; love, as God, muſt be ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, which he extends to his people; he loved his people in Chriſt by way of election defore the foundation of the world; for to this effect <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ.</hi> 1 <hi>v.</hi> 4 and will continue to love them till the world ſhal be no more, and after.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaies, <hi>A friend loves at all times,</hi> Prov. 17. <hi>v.</hi> 17. Now Chriſt is our friend, ſo he has proved himſelf; ſo he cals <hi>Lazarus, John</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>Our friend</hi> Lazarus <hi>ſleepeth.</hi> Such he profeſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be to all his people; ſuch he was to them while his enemies, <hi>Greater love then this has no man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ante om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vitae tempo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e &amp; cùm non crit tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amat &amp; amabit ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os Deus.</note> 
               <hi>that a man ſhould lay down his life for his friends,</hi> John 15.13. Obſerve, Chriſt calls his, <hi>friends,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he died for them; ſo God is ſaid to love them before his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on was ſent, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. Our friend Chriſt loved us before all time, through all time, after all time, or when time ſhall be no more.</p>
            <p>O let me then obtain the love of God,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169877:13"/>and I value not the hatred of the whole kingdom of darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>Ought not we to love this God that loved us firſt, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.19. and continues to loves to the end? therefore neither ſin nor Satan (of which more in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe) ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l finally be able to remove us from <hi>the love of God which is in Chriſt le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> Rom 8. v 2. laſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with ſin and his ſinful peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; hates ſin, but not his people.</note> God does not hate whom he once lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; though they fall into divers and great ſins, he hates their ſins, loves them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; thus God ſeems plainly to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, when he bids the Prophet go love a woman an Adultereſſe, yet beloved of her friend,<note place="margin">Pone te foen inà a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mare moe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantem.</note> 
               <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 1. The woman is the people <hi>Iſrael</hi> committing Idolatry, yet beloved of God; God loved <hi>Solomon</hi> once; therefore <hi>David</hi> called his name <hi>Jedidiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 24, 25. therefore God never hated <hi>Solomon,</hi> notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his ſtrange ſin of Idolatry, unleſſe you'l make him a changling.</p>
            <p>God may juſtly puniſh his beloved for every act of ſin with a temporal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Dilectus. Dominus <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Dilectus à Domino.</note> as he did <hi>Solomon</hi> in his ſon, yet love them; nay becauſe he loves them, therefore he puniſhes, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.2.</p>
            <p>If any object, Chriſtby death has given ſatisfaction for the ſins of his beloved,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169877:13"/>therefore God were unjuſt to take a double account.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt died to take away eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal puniſhments chiefly, yet temporal puniſhments may be mitigated through him, oft quite forgotten by God and not inflicted.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to correct or inſtruct, one being the end of the other. <hi>quae nocent docent.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> But ſecondly know, Chriſt only dyed to ſatisfie for ſin; no created nature can ſatisfie divine wronged juſtice; God pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes his redeemed people not to make ſatisfaction, but to drive them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; his corrections are for inſtruction, not ſatisfaction; <hi>The Lord has torne, come let us return to him and he will heale,</hi> Hoſ. 6. v. 1.</p>
            <p>Farre ſweeter are the corrections of God, then the mercies and embrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the world; <hi>they are as oyle</hi> ſaies the Pſalmiſt, which will not break the head; <hi>if the very righteous ſmite me</hi> (as from God) <hi>it ſhall be a kindneſſe,</hi> Pſal 141. v. 5. The reaſon of Gods loving to the end, is, becauſe he is by nature moſt the ſame. <hi>I am the Lord thy God and change not, therefore yee ſons of</hi> Jacob <hi>are not conſumed,</hi> Mal. 3. v. 6. <hi>with him is no vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſſe nor ſhadow of changing,</hi> Jam. 1. v. 7. thus much his name imports,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Exod. 3.14 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute; ſic Lxx. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> 
               <hi>I Am, the ſame yeſterday, to day and for ever,</hi> Hebr. 13 v, 8.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:169877:14"/>
            <p>Now if God ſhould love one once, and then hate the ſame, God were not the ſame unchangable one.</p>
            <p>But may ſome ſay, <hi>God is ſaid to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> Jonah 2. v 10. <hi>and he repented of the evill</hi> (of puniſhment) <hi>which he ſaid he would do to them</hi>—So <hi>Adam</hi> is threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to die (ſee his ſervant-ike-ſervile condition; undoubtedly Gods childrens now farre beyond it) <hi>in the day thou eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thereof,</hi>
               <note place="margin">non mutar voluntate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſed vult mutatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> yet lived many hundred yeers (ſo that if you conſider how many years he would have been growing to the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he was created in, and adde them, he was the moſt long lived in all the world) ſo <hi>Hezekiah</hi> threatned, yet lives 15. yeers.</p>
            <p>To which I Anſwer, as ſome School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, God changes not his will,<note place="margin">Scriptura loquitur per <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>&amp; ad ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptum no ſtrum.</note> but he willeth a change in others; when he is ſaid to repent, he repents not, but cauſes repentance in others whom he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>Repentance, ſorrow, joy, are not in God, only Scripture uſeth ſuch expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſpeaking to our capacity, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our wont; but God is moſt perfect and free from ſuch paſſions and imperfections. <hi>I am not a man that I ſhould lye, nor the ſonne of man that I
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169877:14"/>ſhould repent,</hi> Numbers 23. v. 19.</p>
            <p>But, this is to be noted (the better to underſtand Gods unchangablenes) that his threatings are conditional;<note place="margin">Mutar ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiam non conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Deus</note> he will bring deſtruction on <hi>Nineve,</hi> unleſſe ſhe repent; on <hi>Ahab,</hi> unleſſe he humble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; on <hi>Abimelech,</hi> unleſſe he reſtore her untouched (on whom <hi>noli me tangere,</hi> was writ) <hi>Sarah;</hi> on <hi>Adam</hi> unleſſe he lay hold on the promiſed ſeed—this condition is expreſſed, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.7, 8. oft times upon repentance, God doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe his ſentence, not change his mind.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, God verified his word in threatning <hi>Adam;</hi> he was condemned to dye the very day he ſinned; and ſo was <hi>Hezekiah;</hi> both dead men according to Law (as we ſay) though repreiv'd for a ſeaſon; but you'l ſay, why doth not God expreſſe the condition alwayes? I anſwer (as another has, in that caſe) It's needleſſe and hurtful; needleſſe,<note place="margin">Qui dedit paenitenti veniam non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſit pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catori pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiam.</note> becauſe expreſſed in <hi>Jeremy;</hi> hurtful, becauſe ſinful and ſecure men hearing God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on repentace will grant pardon, grow the more ſecure, ſuppoſing it time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to repent at any time, as if they could repent at any time, when they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>Having thus cleared the truth, let us
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169877:15"/>ſee more of Chriſts everlaſting love, or loving to perfection (as the Greek bears it.) Chriſt loves his to perfection, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are one with himſelf (&amp; that ſeveral wayes) therefore he will love them till they be perfectly happy and glorious as himſelf.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they are one as father and Son are one; <hi>I deſire,</hi> ſaies Chriſt, <hi>they may be one O Father as we are,</hi> John 17 v. 20, 21. Now Chriſt and his Father are one, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of the ſame nature; and ſo are the Saints one with Chriſt partaking of the very Divine nature, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 4 So that of the Pſalmiſt may even be apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hither,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh</hi> 2.14 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> cha. laſt &amp; v. ult. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>I ſaid yee are gods</hi>—Chriſt in Scripture is called the Father of the Saints, the Word, the incorruptible ſeed; <hi>Paul</hi> ſaies <hi>he travels with them till Chriſt be formed;</hi> Saint <hi>John,</hi> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay they grow,<note place="margin">Hence <hi>Pſ.</hi> 45. thou art fairer, becauſe of Chriſt the Father, or the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad, whoſe glory is the Churches the word fairer</note> &amp; that ſtrong and in meaſure perfect <hi>according to the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Chriſt;</hi> the Saints do as truly (though imperfectly) partake of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Chriſt, as he partook of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man. The nature of Chriſt is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven communicated to them by their new birth, as the child muſt partake of the the nature of his Father; <hi>nonſolum ergo communicando gratiam ſed &amp; participan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169877:15"/>eſſentiam.</hi> To this effect ſee M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Dell</hi> in Com. in <hi>Eſay</hi> 54.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is of a dou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble form to ſhew, or double, that is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent comlineſſe</note>—<hi>So having the ſame nature with Chriſt (Let it, O let it be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with feare, humility and joy) and act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſame ſpirit that Chriſt was, therefore according to grace acting in them, and actuating them, they performe the ſame duties of meekneſſe, patience, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility;</hi> Idem ibidem. Chriſts glory was promiſed (in the time of the Goſpel) to ſhine upon his people, <hi>Eſay</hi> 60. and again thou art a Crown and Diadem of glory, <hi>chap.</hi> 62. <hi>v.</hi> 3. and Chriſt affirms, <hi>John</hi> 17. <hi>v.</hi> 22. the glory God gave him, he gave them; by the ſpirit of the Lord ſayes <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Queſtion. May not a Saint re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the actions flowing from Chr. within No not in the act; tis not the Saints but Chriſts but he may have joy flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from and follow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing the act</note> 
               <hi>we are changed to the ſame Image from glory to glory;</hi> See the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency and beauty of Chriſts children here below! — are they not highly advanced even (in ſomewhat) above Angels? but youl ſay you cann't beleeve that Saints partake of Chriſts nature,— I anſwer, the very ſame oyle which was poured on <hi>Aarons</hi> head, deſcended to the skirts of his cloathing, and the ſame graces poured on Chriſt our head (of whom <hi>Aaron</hi> was a type) come to us the members, changing our nature, from ſons of <hi>Adam, making us ſonnes of God,</hi> though here imperfectly—The grapes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169877:16"/>which the Spies brought out of the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> to <hi>Moſes</hi> were of the ſame nature and kind with thoſe in the Land; ſuch is the money of the earneſt, and that of the full wages; therefore what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever priviledge the Saints have in the true Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> heaven; whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſon-ſhip, divine nature, glory they ſhall be partakers of there, they ſhall have a taſte of here; the ſame ſpirit is the earneſt here and joy hereafter: Chriſt and his people are one, as the Vine and the branches; <hi>I am the Vine, yee are the branches,</hi> John 5. Now the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, tree, root, partake of the ſame juyce and fatneſſe; 'tis even ſo between Chriſt and his people.</p>
            <p>Chriſt and his are one as head and members; the ſame ſoule enlivens the head and members; from the head come ſpirits to quicken the body, from Chriſt encreaſe of graces in his people, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.16. and while he's alive, the Saints muſt live. <hi>John</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.19 for while life is in the head, death is not in the members; Chriſt will not ſuffer his limbs to be loſt, and as unlikely 'tis to have dead members; he will love and cheriſh them, being part of his myſtical ſelf.</p>
            <p>Chriſt and his are one, as husband and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169877:16"/>wife, his honour is hers: if he a King, ſhe a Queen; his goods, glory, hers; <hi>ubi tu Caius ego ibi Caia.</hi> If Chriſt ours, all ours, whether <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Apollo</hi> life or death, things preſent or to come; his death me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, reſurrection, all are ours, becauſe we Chriſts Spouſe, and he the heire of all.</p>
            <p>Hence learn (in a digreſſion) that if Chriſt be thy husband, O Saint, what e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thou owed'ſt before marriage or ſince, Chriſt thy now husband muſt, nay has payd all. If Satan accuſe thee for any debt, ſay thou haſt nothing to do in it, bid him go to thy husband, Chriſt.</p>
            <p>No Divorce ever to be between them; the Lord hates putting away, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.16. though for the hardneſſe of the Jewes hearts he ſuffered it yet from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning it was not ſo. Sin may for a time ſeemingly ſeparate, not Finally.</p>
            <p>Chriſt and his are one, as the chief cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtone &amp; the reſt make one building; the corner ſtone and the reſt are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the ſame nature. Stones are oft trod upon; as Chriſt, the living<note n="*" place="margin">Eſay tels us <hi>chap.</hi> 54 <hi>ver.</hi> 11.12. How God will have the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Church of precious not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſtone, as thoſe in the firſt Temple; the living ſtones the Saints are Carbuncles, Agates and Saphires. So that in this ſenſe, the glory of the ſecond Temple doth exceed the glory of the firſt.</note> ſtones muſt learn to endure; ſtones in the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding uphold one the other, to teach us
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169877:17"/>to bear one anothers burdens; Stones in the building are knit together with morter, to teach us how love yoakes, knits, cements Saints together.</p>
            <p>To conclude this point with a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral uſe, Conſider as Chriſt and his people are one theſe ſeverall wayes, ſo all love to perfection as Chriſt his. The father loves the child and deſires its life and proſperity — the husband the wife, and deſires her continuance, not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce — the head loves the members, and deſires not parting but perfection the chief corner ſtone, and the reſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to keep together to hold up the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; the corner ſtone deſires not to ſhrink from the reſt, but delights in a compleated edifice; the Vine and bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches mutually clip, embrace and love each other; ſhe covets the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of her branches, deſires not to have them lopt of or to live like a mother childernleſſe.</p>
            <p>Chriſt loves his for ever, becauſe ſin which may ſeem to part him and them is ſlaine (ſo it cannot provoke him to give them a bill of divorce) and that three wayes; <hi>judicially,</hi> for 'tis condemned to dye both by Chriſt and his people, ſo 'tis dead according to Law, which is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to a Chriſtian that his greateſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169877:17"/>ſin (nay and Satan) is condemned to die, and ſhall not for ever Rivall with him. See death threatned, that threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a ſentencing, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13. <hi>ver.</hi> 14. <hi>O death, I will be thy plagues, O grave I will be thy deſtruction.</hi> Now if death and the grave (the effects of ſin) be deſtroyed, then muſt ſin that cauſes both, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle quotes the ſenſe of that place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55. <hi>O death where is thy ſting?</hi> that is Sin; Sentenced (and more) now, though not fully put to death til her after</p>
            <p>Secondly ſin is dead <hi>civilly,</hi> becauſe the power of it is much abated, its domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and tyranny overpowred; thus <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim</hi> is ſaid to be dead by the Prophet <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. <hi>When</hi> Ephraim (that is the King of the Tribe of <hi>Ephraim</hi>) <hi>ſpake trembling,</hi> the people even trembled at his voice; but when he offended in <hi>Baal</hi> by ſerving <hi>Baal,</hi> he dyed, in reſpect of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience not yeilded to him as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; thus thoſe fel creatures which in inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency would tremblingly obey <hi>Adam</hi> (or rather lovingly) when he diſobeyed God, they renounced obeyſance to him or his Soveraignty; and he civilly dyed, even the ſame day he ſinned; thus ſayes the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>account your ſelves dead to ſinne,</hi> Rom. 6.11. Thus every good Chriſtian
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169877:18"/>eſteems ſin dead, not to be obeyed, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> yeilding to it or acknowledging it Chriſt has dealt with ſin in part, as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Philiſtines did with <hi>Iſrael;</hi> they had no Smith to make ſword or ſpeare, only, file for fork<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and mattocks; he leaves ſin no deadly weapon, it can fray us, not<note n="*" place="margin">Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rata Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti morte.</note> ſlay us.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, naturally ſin is ſlaine, Chriſt has given it its death<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s wound (by his death &amp; reſurrection) it can't live long though it may linger a while in a Saint; as a Tree that is cut at the root with a ſore gaſh or two muſt dye within a yeer, perhaps within a month or two, though for the preſent it may have leaves and fruit, it ſecretly dies and will ſuddainly ſhew it ſelfe withered.</p>
            <p>Wouldſt thou know whether ſin dye in thee or no? Doeſt thou when Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer comes (I mean temptation) bring forth fruit of ſin or no? If thou doeſt not, thou art dead to ſin, ſin is dying in thee.</p>
            <p>Chriſt (that for the future his people ſin not to hinder his everlaſting love) gives them preventing grace, heales their nature, reſtraines them (them whom he redeemed) by his word from ſin, ſhewing them the deformity of it the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169877:18"/>reward of it; perchance ſometime pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding to them the glory of heaven, and above all the<note n="*" place="margin">If there were nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a hell to puniſh, nor a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, the Saints would love Chriſt Yet as in Moſes and our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward may be lookt at, to ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>ver.</hi> 26 <hi>&amp;</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>Non pleno ſed ſemiple. no anima.</hi>
               </note> love of Chriſt dehorts from ſin by the voice of his ſpirit, the voice behind, that when they are about to ſin, ſayes, this is the way, walk ye in it; That we walke more in his feare, enjoy more of his favour. St. <hi>John</hi> ſayes <hi>he that is born of God ſins not</hi> (unto death, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly and conſtantly.) In a choyce garden weedes may grow up without the conſent of the gard'ner, againſt his will. <hi>Sin in a Saint</hi> borne of God is as thoſe weedes, not of his own ſowing nor of his own growing willingly; to whom he intends a day of weeding. A Saint can't ſin unto death becauſe of the holy ſeed, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 9. In an Oake in winter we ſee (ſeemingly at the leaſt) death, but there is juyce to conſerve it in the root, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 6. <hi>ver. ult.</hi> (though that text has another meaning) ſo Chriſt our root by the juyce of his word, grace, the holy ſeed, keeps us from ſining to death; then we have life (like the Oak) in the winter or more dangerous time of ſinne when we ſeem even dead.</p>
            <p>We may ſay of death the effect of ſin, and ſin the cauſe of death, as the ſons of the Prophets, death is in the pot (Sin is
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169877:19"/>in our nature) put in flower, wheat ground, or Chriſt bruiſed for our ſins, and all is well; the ſons of the Prophets the Saints need not feare.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts hold ſin in a Saint Veniall; but with judicious <hi>Calvin</hi> we affirm all deadly;<note place="margin">Omne peccatum mortale eſt, quia adverſus dei volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellio eſt, &amp; legis praevaricatio in quam edictum eſt ſine exceptione dei judicium. Sanctorum delicta venialia eſſe non ex ſuapte natura, ſed quia e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i miſericordia veniam conſequuntur, <hi>Calvin, Libroz. cap.</hi> 8 <hi>ſect. ultima.</hi>
               </note> becauſe tis rebellion againſt God; but thus far Veniall, becauſe Chriſt has ſatisfied for the ſins of all his (of ſome even before their actuall committing) ſo they, ſince God is juſt, be pardoned.</p>
            <p>That there is a reſtraining grace in the Saints, ſo that they ſin not ſo eagerly as before, nor ſo oft, to remove (if it were poſſible) Chriſts love finally from them, ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. <hi>ver.</hi> 3. Which forgiveth all thy ſin and healeth all thy diſeaſes, that that the wound burſt not forth to a new ſore. So <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. Take away all iniquity and give grace, <hi>vid.</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine (as ſome read it) or as <hi>ver.</hi> 4. I will heale their back-ſlidings.—</p>
            <p>God will love his people to the end; for though they have ſin,<note place="margin">Num. 23.21.</note> yet he will not behold their ſin as to condemn them for
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169877:19"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, neither indeed can he, ſince Chriſt has ſafeguarded them, ſatisfying for them, though he may bring, as is ſaid, a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral puniſhment for every act of ſin; yet am not ignorant how many affirm, ſince Chriſt has ſatisfied, the Saints ſufferings are (only) exerciſes of faith &amp; trials, not puniſhments. But <hi>Jeremy</hi> in behalf of the captive people (whereof ſome ſure Saints) ſeeming to correct any private murmuring againſt Gods puniſhing hand, proves the truth of the point,<note place="margin">Non ſolum non malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Moabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas &amp; eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum regent in vob is non vidi. Verum ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que veſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> O <hi>Iſrael</hi> pee catum, ſed filium pro te peccatum factum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debo. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictionem immittere decrevi, naminferni Portae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travos non valere p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terint.</note> 
               <hi>ex Lament.</hi> 3.39. <hi>Why doth a living man complaine,</hi> for the puniſhing of ſin? Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel texts hold forth the ſame.</p>
            <p>But to returne to the confeſſion of the Sorcerer <hi>Balaam</hi> (as the famous D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Hall,</hi> cals him) <hi>Numb.</hi> 23. <hi>v.</hi> 21. he hath not beheld iniquity—<hi>Jacobs</hi> ſinne ſhall not be looked on by me (but my Sons death) to cauſe a curſe on my people, <hi>Non maledixit populo Deus; non ergò peccatum in iis videret.</hi> Parallel is that of <hi>Mica.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 18. <hi>Who is a God like unto thee, that pardoneth iniquity, and paſſeth by tranſgreſſion?</hi> (not ſeeing it) as <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.20. <hi>In thoſe dayes they ſhall look for the ſin of</hi> Judah, <hi>but it ſhall no where be found—for I will pardon whom I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve;</hi> their ſins ſhall not prevail to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169877:20"/>to ruine them or curſe them; I will not behold their ſin, but being ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied in my Son, will paſſe by it; his death ſhall prevail to divert oft tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral — judgments, ever, eternal curſes. See <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. <hi>v.</hi> 35, 36. If the Sun and Moon can ceaſe to be, or the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and the earth be meaſured, then my people (typifying the Church) ſhall ceaſe to be a Nation, for what they have done. And what had they not done?</p>
            <p>I ſay, by way of repetition, Chriſt loves his to the end; knowing a full ſatisfaction to be paid for their offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; ſo though their ſins in themſelves (never ſo much mortified) be deadly, yet cannot damne, becauſe redeemed, and muſt obtaine mercy — the word of God is Salt, and keeps his people from ſtinking in his noſtrils; the word is truth, and ſanctifies all his; Chriſt is a Sun, and that of righteouſneſſe; now the Sun exhales corrupt vapours, that the ſea and waters corrupt not; even ſo <hi>behold the Lamb of God that taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſins of the World,</hi> both guilt and puniſhment, <hi>healing our nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt was made ſinne for us, and a ſacrifice for ſinne, <hi>Eſay</hi> 53, 10. So
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169877:20"/>that in the Saints, in ſome ſenſe, there needs no conſcience of ſin (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) — <hi>ex Hebr.</hi> 10.2. Chriſt being a moſt perfect Sacrifice for them.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Sacrifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um &amp; pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum.</note> Not but that Saints make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of ſinning, nay hate it; <hi>what have I to do any more with Idols?</hi> ſayes <hi>Ephraim</hi> pardoned, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.8. They live in a higher ſpheare then the men of the world. No leſſe then Angels food (as 'tis called, becauſe food even fit for Angels, could they eate) will ſerve their turne, I meane the true meat from Heaven; they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn huskes, ſinne, traſh, being come home by repentance to their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>But the ſoules of the Saints need not be grieved, or conſciences trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled (in regard of hell) for ſin, becauſe of Chriſts Sacrifice.</p>
            <p>Will Chriſt leave theſe finally, for whom he has been a Sacrifice? He will not, nor can they him; the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in Scripture rendred to <hi>forſake,</hi> as <hi>Math.</hi> 27.46. cant be applied in a ſtrict ſenſe, becauſe Chriſt never forſakes his; nor did the father, Chriſt on the Croſſe; only leaves for a while.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:169877:21"/>
            <p>Sin then cant make Chriſt leave his people; if that could, why did it not, when by ſinne they had forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves in <hi>Adam,</hi> and were by it deformed, polluted, ugly? He that loved them then, will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to love them, being moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable.</p>
            <p>I have a little turned aſide already to ſee why man, the buſh, not burnt, though fired by ſin; i'le go a little neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and ſee this wonder, and the love of Chriſt the cauſe. —</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle writing to the <hi>Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, chap.</hi> 3.19. Being in an holy ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of Chriſts love, affirmes it to paſſe knowledge.— That God who is the eternall being ſhould love man when hee had ſcarce a being, nor ever could have had, but through him; and when he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited himſelfe through diſobedience, and made himſelfe perfectly miſerable, worſe then nothing, God ſhould be enamoured with deformity. For what is more deformed then ſin? It ſeemes ſuch was and is Gods tranſcendent love that mans extream miſery could not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate it; the deploredneſſe of mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, did but heighten the holy flame
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169877:21"/>of Chriſts love, 'tis as high as heaven, who can reach it? 'tis as low as hell, who can underſtand it? Heaven (through its glory) could not containe him (man being miſerable) nor hels torments make him refrain, ſuch was his perfect love.</p>
            <p>That Chriſts love ſhould extend to his enemies, and ſhould long after them that rebelled againſt him, yea not only ſo, but hugge them in his armes; lodge them in his boſome, is the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt improvement of love.</p>
            <p>That thoſe moſt excellent creatures the once glorious Angels, ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be recovered, never looſed from thoſe everlaſting chains; and vile ſinful duſt, man, ſhould be redeemed, as tis the envy of thoſe wretched ſpirits, ſo the admiration of Saints and Angels.</p>
            <p>That Chriſt ſhould come from the eternall boſome of his father, to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of ſorrow and death, that God ſhould be manifeſted in the fleſh, the Creator made a creature (behold the Gods come to us in the likenes of fleſh <hi>Act.</hi> 14.11. And<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> dwell with fleſh, <hi>Dan,</hi> 2.11.) that he that was cloathed with glory ſhould be wrapped with rags of fleſh; he that filled heaven be
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169877:22"/>cradled in a manger; that the power of God ſhould flye from weak man, the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> into <hi>Egypt;</hi> that the God of the Law ſhould be ſubject to the Law; the God of Circumciſion cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed; the God that made the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, buſie working (as is ſuppoſed) at the homely Trade of <hi>Joſeph;</hi> that he who commanded the divels to their chains, ſhould be tempted; that he whoſe is the world and the fullneſſe thereof, ſhould hunger and thirſt; that the God of ſtrength ſhould be weary; the Judge of all fleſh condemned; the God of life put to death, (the deare Son of God ſtrugling with his Fathers wrath) that he that is one with his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhould cry out of miſery, <hi>my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, my Father,</hi> — that he that had the keyes of hell and death, ſhould lye impriſon'd in the Sepulcher of another, having in his life time nowhere to lay his head, nor after death to lay his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; and all this for mans ſake; is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the thought of created natures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If this goodly frame of Creation</hi> (ſayes the Biſhop of <hi>Norwich</hi>) <hi>ſhould runne back to its firſt confuſion, or be reduced to its firſt nothing,</hi> (though a moſt ſtrange change) <hi>'twere not ſo high a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169877:22"/>wonder as for God to become man, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer being of things finite, the latter of an infinite ſubject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The glorious Angels could not but wonder to ſee their Creator humbled below themſelves, and humanity ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, by Chriſts aſſuming it, which <hi>Peter</hi> hints at, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. Which the Angels deſire to look into. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>tranſlatio ſùmpta ab iis qui prono corpore oculos admovent at rem ownem propius &amp; acuratius cognoſoant,</hi> ſayes <hi>Beza.</hi> Yea ſo look into, as to ſound (if it were poſſible) the depth of this love.</p>
            <p>To ſee that head (before which the Angels caſt down themſelves and worſhipped (as I may ſay) crowned with thornes:<note place="margin">Caput an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelic is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritibus tremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitate ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronatum. <hi>Bernard.</hi>
               </note> and thoſe eyes purer then the Sun, put out by the darkneſſe of death; thoſe eares which heare nothing (to ſpeak to capacity) but Hallelujah's of Saints and Angels, to heare the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies of the multitude; that face which was fairer then the ſons of men, (for being born and conceived with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin, he was free from the contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous effect of it, deformity, and was moſt perfectly beautiful) to be ſpit on, by thoſe beaſtly, wretched Jewes; that mouth and tongue that <hi>ſpake as never
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169877:23"/>man ſpake,</hi> accuſed for falſe doctrine, nay blaſphemy (let the Miniſters of that Maſter take falſe accuſations patiently; <hi>For if they have called the Maſter of the houſe</hi> Baalzebub, <hi>what ſhall they not ſay to his ſervants?</hi>)</p>
            <p>Thoſe hands which freely ſwayed the Scepter of Heaven, nayled to the croſſe; thoſe feet like unto fine braſſe (which in the Prophet <hi>Zacharies</hi> ſenſe, <hi>ch. ult. v.</hi> 4.) ſhall ſtand upon the mount of Olives or thereabout, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as ſome ſay) the middle of the world, and the place where Chriſt was condemned, to judge the world) nayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Croſſe for mans ſins; each ſenſe annoyed; his feeling or touching with a ſpear and nayles; his ſmell with ſtinking ſavour, being crucified about <hi>Golgotha, the place of ſculs</hi> (whereof ſome might be green,) his taſte with Vinegar and Gall,<note place="margin">Anima eſt aeque ubi amat ac ubi animat.</note> his hearing with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, and ſight with his mother and Diſciples bemoaning him, his ſoul ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly comfortleſſe and forſaken, is able to ſtrike amazement to thoſe excellent creatures. <hi>Calvine</hi> judiciouſly affirmes Gods love and care in providing all for man before he made him, conclud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he would not forget him now he
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169877:23"/>was made; but much more of Gods love in Chriſt, is to be ſeen in provide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heaven for man, when he was not, and when after, moſt ſinfull; the joyes of a man in Chriſt, <hi>eare has not heard, eye hath not ſeene, nor entred into mans heart to conceive,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. <hi>v.</hi> 9. thoſe joyes are like the new name, <hi>which no man knowes but he that has it,</hi> Revel. 2. <hi>v.</hi> 17. but the joyes in heaven with Chriſt exceed; the Apoſtle that was there, ſayes, <hi>they are not to be uttered,</hi> but <hi>unſpeakable;</hi> and moſt likely, ſince out of love provided by ſuch infinite wiſdome; we ſee the pavement of that glorious edifice, how beſpangled with lights; but what then muſt the inner glory thereof be? I ſay modeſtly of it, as one did, <hi>I will not too earneſtly covet to know its glory before I come there, leſt ſtriving to know its glory, I forget the, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ay thither; then my loſſe will ſeeme greater, knowing the greatneſſe of the loſſe.</hi> But with a parentheſis, <hi>I know whom I have beleeved, and am verily perſwaded he will keep me ſafe, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent me ſpotleſſe at that day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider what moſt intolerable (yet to be undergone) and everlaſting and moſt exquiſite paines Chriſt out of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169877:24"/>love has delivered his from! What ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſlaking tortures! what mercileſſe furie of unweariable tormentors! what utter deſpaire of any poſſibility of releaſe! what never dying death! ever renewing torments! never pitied, never intermitted damnation!</p>
            <p>His love appears in giving his, his guard of Angels <hi>to keep them in all their wayes;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bernard</hi> dixit. Bonus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelus videt; te peccan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem &amp; do<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let; malus &amp; gaudet, &amp; cave; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us videt qui judicat ergo ne pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> thoſe which wait upon his own throne, guard the cottages of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.7. Whether each Saint has his Angel, I affirm not, ſaies <hi>Calvin;</hi> yet two places ſeem plain, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.10. <hi>their Angels behold</hi>—and <hi>Acts</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>'tis his Angel.</hi> See the Churches opinion, then; how ever, 'tis certaine the Angels take care of them, put good thoughts into the ſoules which the Spirit muſt ſanctifie; why ſhall not they be allowed to put good thoughts into us, as well as the Divel bad? they oft reſiſt Satan (unknown to the Saints) when he would elſe appear to fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, nay to devoure;<note place="margin">See the Jearned M. <hi>Leigh</hi> on the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> thus <hi>Daniel</hi> may be underſtood, 12.1. Then ſtood up <hi>Michael</hi> your Prince which is for the people; for though Chriſt may be meant oft by <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangel, yet the Archangel is uſed diſtinct from Chriſt.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169877:24"/>1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.16. the Lord ſhal, deſcend (ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Chriſt) with a ſhout the voyce of the (rather of an Archangel. Maſter <hi>Perkins</hi> We read Chriſt ſhal come with his holy Angels; are not the Angels di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from Chriſt? Now (by the by) If one Archangel, why not more? the Jewes rekon ſeven, <hi>Michael, Gabriel, Raphael, Daniel</hi>—but to omit their teſtimony in <hi>Daniel</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 13. <hi>Michael</hi> is called one of the chiefe Princes, or the firſt; one implies more, a firſt, a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond. <hi>David</hi> ſtirs up himſelf by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Angels prayſing God, the true meaning of that Pſalme, 103. <hi>v.</hi> 20. but whom means he they excell in ſtrength? man? that were no honour, hee's but duſt, they excel not only the wicked ſpirits, but one another, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellers are Archangels; <hi>Peter</hi> ſaies as much; compare <hi>Peter</hi> with <hi>Jude</hi> 9. the Angels excelling in ſtrength bring nota railing accuſation, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Iude</hi> ſaies, <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangel did not bring a railing accuſation, quoting the ſame<note n="*" place="margin">Satan branded <hi>Moſes</hi> for a murderer becauſe of the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, though hee was in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from God, but his brethren underſtood it not, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.25. and would have the murderer his ſepulchre known, becauſe a murderer; but his aime was that Iſrael moſt prone to Idolatry, might worſhip and Idolize the bones and Sepulchre.</note> ſtory, the ſame Agents or Diſputants;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169877:25"/>onely one in the ſingular number, the other the plural; <hi>A Habr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſme;</hi> one Goſpel ſaies theeves railed on Chriſt, the other, one of the theeves; thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand <hi>Revel.</hi> 4.5. of the ſeven ſpirits before the throne, not becauſe ſeven is a perfect number in Scripture, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that number uſed, not underſtand <hi>ſeptemplicem ſpiritus operationem qui tamen in ſe uniſſimus eſt,</hi> but underſtand ſeven ſpirits or Archangels, being more agreeable to that place; ſo underſtand <hi>Job</hi> 38 <hi>v.</hi> 7. when morning ſtars ſang together, and ſons of God ſhouted for joy. There are no morning ſtars, but one <hi>Venus;</hi> ſometime ſhe is the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtar, ſometime the evening; nor were ſtars created till the fourth day; therefore could not ſing at laying the foundation of the earth, as theſe in <hi>Job</hi> did; again, ſtars cannot properly be ſaid to ſing; remember the chief of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels is called <hi>Lucifer,</hi> the, or, a, morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtar.<note place="margin">Eſa. 14.12.</note> Laſtly, God had at laying the foundation of the earth, no other ſons but Angels, man not created long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; by morning ſtars Archangels are to be underſtood, as excelling, by ſons of God, Angels, Gods ſons by creation.</p>
            <p>Envine not man and his guard on
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169877:25"/>earth, more guarded then<note n="*" place="margin">Sine cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtode metu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum est, multomajus a cuſtode est metuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum. <hi>C.A.</hi> dixit.</note> regarded; thy guard, O beloved, love thee, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce at mans good, <hi>are thouſands of thouſands, and ten thouſand times ten thouſand,</hi> Dan. 7. v. 10. had we our eyes opened as <hi>Eliſha's</hi> ſervant, we ſhould ſee more for us then againſt us. How great is man, O Lord, <hi>how haſt thou in love viſited him?</hi> After this life, they like Chariot and horſes of fire, convoy the ſoul of the Saint as conquerour, through Chriſt, to heaven; mark, what an honourable and ſafe convoy the bleſſed ſouls have;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> proves the Saints a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the truth from falſhood, Chriſt fró Antichriſt and to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome—becauſe of this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynting of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, 1 <hi>John cap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 13 &amp; 20. <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas enim eſt index ſui &amp; obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui.</hi>
               </note> little doth the world think what a noble perſon it abuſes, when it abuſes a Saint.</p>
            <p>Think not O Saint, I wrong Chriſt by ſaying he is not the Archangel only uſed in Scripture; behold I rather praiſe him, ſhewing his glory in his glorious creatures. Chriſts love appears in giving his people his holy ſpirit, as he has fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced them without, ſo he has ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened them within to reſiſt and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come; hence thoſe ſoveraign graces to ſtand in time of temptation, to be heartned againſt all doubts and feares, aſſured of Chriſts love and ſalvation, enabled to cry <hi>Abba Father;</hi> ſo in the might of God, his people may bid defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169877:26"/>to the gates of hell, let all princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities and powers, rulers of darknes do their worſt, his people in right of him whoſe they are, are above their malice, though weak in themſelves, ſtrong in him; ſinful in themſelves, but Chriſt is their righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>How canſt thou be but comforted O Chriſtian, that haſt the holy ſpirit the Comforter with thee? I will ſhew thee in a word or two (by way of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion) <hi>Be of good comfort,</hi> ſaies Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 16. <hi>ult. I have overcome the world,</hi> which would diſcomfort thee. Chriſt ſpeaks it, who ſpeaks not to the eare only as man, but to the heart and ſoul; he ſaies, be circumciſed and repent, ſpeaking to the elect, yet in ſin; not that they have a power to repent—no more then the world had to be made, when he ſaid, <hi>let it be</hi>— or then <hi>Lazarus</hi> being dead, to whom he ſaid, <hi>come forth,</hi> to ariſe; but becauſe he gives power with his word, to the elect, to the world, to <hi>Lazarus,</hi> to repent, to be made, to riſe from the dead; conſider who bids; Chriſt; againſt whom all ſin (with the Father—) is committed; he who is Judge, he bids; then thy ſinnes need not caſt thee down; <hi>be of good
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169877:26"/>cheere daughter,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>for thy ſinnes be forgiven thee, thy faith has made thee whole,</hi> Luke 8.48 <hi>Who now ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn, ſince Chriſt juſtifies?</hi> Rom. 8.33. I am neer that juſtifie, who will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with thee? <hi>Eſay</hi> 50.8. Survey thy adverſaries, who can diſmay thee?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who art thou that art afraid of a man? (I, even I am he that comfort you) of man whoſe breath is in his noſtrils, and forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt me thy Maker? of man that is as graſſe, and of the ſon of man that ſhall die?</hi> Eſay 51.12, 13. Remember O Saint, God tels thee man is graſſe; conſider God gives graſſe good ground to grow in, Sun to cheriſh, dew and rain to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; though the oppreſſor has the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of the world, fear him not; God can bleſſe outwardly as he did <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and curſe inwardly and ſecretly; the meat of God being in their mouths, the wrath of God may be upon the weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt of them. I have read of a light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that hurts not the ſcabberd, yet melts the ſword; but conſider <hi>Eſay</hi> 50. <hi>v.</hi> 9. <hi>they ſhall waxe old as a garment;</hi> like a garment, ſo the oppreſſour may be in faſhion (nay and do God ſervice for the preſent) but,<note place="margin">Simonides in vitam humanam.</note> ſhall ſuddenly be out of date, as an old ſute of cloaths,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169877:27"/>another ſhall come in the rome.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>One generation paſſeth away and another cometh.</hi> Shall Satan diſcomfort thee? true, he loves to impriſon Chriſts peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but Chriſt having the Keyes of hell,<note place="margin">Delphis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racula ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant. juven. Plutarch. de defectu oraculorum Cicero lib. <hi>2.</hi> de divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione <hi>ſpeaks of oracles ceaſing. All the Idols of Egypt (when Chriſt was there) fell down of their own accord</hi>— polid. poſtea quam Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus colitur (<hi>ſaies the wicked</hi> Por phyrius) nihil utili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis a diis conſequi poſſumus.</note> grave, death, none of his can be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned without conſent; but wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed creatures, Chriſt has ſpoyled princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities and powers, triumphing over them, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 15. By dying, his death ſpoyled Satans kingdom.</p>
            <p>There is ſtory in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> how one <hi>Thamus an Aegyptian being in a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calmed ſhip at ſea, a voyce came to him, commanding him (though with ſorrow) to proclaime (at a certaine place he ſayled by) the death of great god</hi> Pan; <hi>which he having accordingly done, there followed much ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5+ letters">
                     <desc>•••••…</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g, crying, howling, lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion. Pan</hi> was Chriſt the great Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of our ſouls who (upon ſearch is found to have) dyed about that time, and ſo ruined Satan. Chriſts very birth frightned him from oraculizing, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. the Divels own confeſſion; But however, Satan could only bruiſe the heel of Chriſt people.</p>
            <p>Chriſt is onely able to comfort,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169877:27"/>earthly and creature-comforts are but as the white of an Egge in <hi>Iob</hi> without taſte; Chriſt will, nay has ſent the ſpirit, the comforter <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. A ſpirit can only comfort a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; he comes skipping over moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of ſin and obſtacles to aſſiſt; he puts by <hi>Mary Magdalens</hi> over-curious touch (though ſhe had ſo long waited about the Sepulchre to ſee him, or to hear news of him) to haſten comfort to his penſive Diſciples and ſad <hi>Peter; Go,</hi> ſaies Chriſt, haſte to my Diſciples, tell them (and <hi>Peter</hi>) that has denied me thrice, that I am alive; that as I dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their ſins—ſo I am aroſe for their juſtification.</p>
            <p>Chriſt was annoynted for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to comfort—<hi>Eſay</hi> 61.2. he has balme of Gilead for a ſorrowful ſpirit, and oyle of comfort for thoſe that mourn in Sion; he has promiſed to ſend the Comforter, <hi>John</hi> 14.17. and though he is not bound to man, to make good his promiſe—yet becauſe God, if we beleeve not, that is, if we ſtagger through weakneſſe at the promiſe, he continues faithful and cannot deny himſelf, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2, 12, 13. he has prayed to the Father, and therefore ye ſhall be
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169877:28"/>comforted, <hi>John</hi> 14.16. — creature comforts are like feaſts of a Funeral, ſeem indeed to gild ſorrow over, or flatter woe, but are indeed as <hi>Iob's,</hi> but miſerable comforters; we ſay as <hi>Rachel, give me children or I die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object</hi> I have waited, but he comes not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt loves thee, therefore when he ſees time he will come and will not tarry; wait his leaſure, he is they Creator, thy Maſter, thy Husband; thou haſt much ſinned againſt him, he would have come to thee with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of information oft, but thou didſt refuſe; now thou wouldſt have him come to thee with the ſpirit of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation; if he would not at all, he ſerv'd thee well enough, but he will come; then wait, thou maiſt perceive thou haſt his ſpirit in ſome meaſure in that thou doſt endure; elſe with <hi>Iudas</hi> or <hi>Achitophel,</hi> thou wouldſt end thy dayes. We truſt our Phyſician when we are very low, yet he brings us lower, he thinks us not low enough for a comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table cordial; God perchance ſees thee not empty enough of creature-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, not humble enough (for many are humbled, yet not humble) believe him, he will yet come and raiſe up. If
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169877:28"/>a Merchant having a ſhip at ſea, could certainly be perſwaded it would come home ſafe and rich, he patiently would wait its arrival, though it be abſent long; as God is true, beleeve his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; as Chriſt has been touched with the ſame infirmities, remember his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion; he is one with thee, therefore thou canſt not long be comfortleſſe; he being happy, he deſires not to drink of the fruit of the Vine alone, that is, to partake of glory, or the comforts of the ſpirit, compared to cheriſhing wine, but to drink it with his diſciples.</p>
            <p>Chriſt's are his Temple, there are Hymns and ſpiritual Songs, he dwels in his people; how can ſorrow, or not comfort be there, where the God of all comfort and conſolation is? Art thou afflicted for his cauſe? Behold Chriſt with the three children in the furnace. Art thou unmindful of Gods viſiting his people by Angels (ſometimes by Chriſt in their ſhape) and doth he not viſit thee with the ſpirit who is above An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels? <hi>as is his name, ſo is he;</hi> Immanuel <hi>is his name, and God is with us;</hi> the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple negation may confirme the point, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 5. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>I will never, never never, forſake thee.</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:169877:29"/>No wonder then Saint <hi>Paul</hi> bids the Saints rejoyce alwaies, <hi>I ſay rejoyce, Phil.</hi> 4.4. Could <hi>Caeſar</hi> think to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and encourage the fearful Pilo tin the dangerous ſtorme, by ſaying <hi>quid times nauta? Caeſarem vehis.</hi> Feare not, <hi>Caeſar</hi> is thy fare; and not rather the Saints, which (as the Diſciples once had Chriſt aboard) have Chriſt to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand wind and waves, who is with them to the end of the world, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher gave thanks that he was born in the time of true Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy</note> How happy are we to be born in ſuch a time, not only in reſpect of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection — but information! the Lord doth <hi>effundere ſpiritum,</hi> not <hi>de ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu,</hi> pour forth his ſpirit, not ſend drops as in the Law (though ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar men had the ſpirit in abundance) but ſhowers; not only the day-ſtar, but the Sun of righteouſneſſe is riſen upon his people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Object.</note> Ought we not then to pray ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teporally, or by the ſpirit? <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays <hi>in multiloquio non deeſſe peccatum, in the multitude of words there lacks no ſin, Prov.</hi> 10.19. and bids not be raſh with our mouths, but that our <hi>words be few, Eccl.</hi> 5.2. the Diſciples deſire our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to teach them to pray as <hi>Iohn</hi> did his (intimaing a form) and our Saviour,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169877:29"/>in one Goſpel, ſaies to them, <hi>when yee pray</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſay, abſolutely, <hi>Our Father which art in heaven</hi>—not after this manner; and bids them not uſe <hi>vaine repetitions,</hi> or <hi>much ſpeaking:</hi> himſelf when he prayed uſed the ſame words, and was known by breaking of bread, as uſing one form; beſides in the law forms were uſed by command from <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note> Whether was there that free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the time of the Law, when we were under age, differing not from children, as now when the ſpirit pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully teacheth with boldneſſe to cry <hi>Abba, Father?</hi> ſo the time of the Law to the time of the Goſpel not compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; ſee <hi>Perkins</hi> on <hi>Galat.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>A child, though heire of all, while under age, differeth not from a ſervant.</hi> Whether <hi>Solomon</hi> be not to be underſtood of common talk and vain, rather then prayer; whether ſons adopted having the ſpirit to guide (with ſome preme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation) need uſe or do uſe raſhneſſe— whether <hi>Iohn</hi> or our Saviours teaching their Diſciples a form then, were not more needful then now, conſidering their ignorance (which the Goſpels make known) and need of an <hi>A. B. C.</hi> conſidering the then not deſcent of the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:169877:30"/>ſpirit to teach and inſtruct them — whether after, the Diſciples uſed ever that form; <hi>Peter</hi> uſes another, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.24.31. —though that form is a moſt full, pithy prayer for ſo ſhort an one; yet whether he that ſtirs up the gift of the ſpirit in him by exerciſe, praying longer, reverently, carefully, offend; whether thoſe repetitions forbidden, were as ours; expreſſions of zeal and affection,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and not rather ſuch as <hi>Battus</hi> uſed (an old fooliſh Poet, who to fill up his Verſes would ſtuffe in any what) as <hi>O vid</hi> quotes him,
<q>—Montibus inquit erant, &amp; erant in montibus illis.</q> whether our Saviours uſing the ſame words,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Luk. 24.35</note> were not rather an ejaculation and a zealous repetition or expreſſion of his ſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow, rather then a proof for a ſet form; Whether our Saviour was not known in breaking bread (juſt at that time the ſpirit made him known) rather then by breaking bread as a form, I leave to the indifferent Reader to judge.</p>
            <p>Second <hi>Anſw.</hi> 'Tis not he that prayes moſt readily and fluently that has the gift of prayer, he only is the beſt rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torician; for I dare ſay, a wicked man
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:169877:30"/>having texts of Scripture <hi>ad unguem,</hi> as he may be ready in the letter (wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thoſe Jewes, who can tell how oft a word is uſed in the Law and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets) ſhall pray as fully, as earneſtly as any, yet not feelingly from Chriſt within; ſome lip-labour only 'tis to ſuch; he prayes by the ſpirit, that from Chriſt within, touched with the feeling of his own wants, ſhall according to Scripture rule, ſend the embaſſage of his ſoul to God, and treat with him by faith in humility concerning his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and his Churches good; ſince Chriſt has poured out his ſpirit upon his people, why ſhould not his people poure forth their ſoul to God? as <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah</hi>—did, and not by form, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 15.</p>
            <p>Cannot every child ſay <hi>Abba Father!</hi> or ſhall nature teach her children to ask what they need, and not grace alſo?</p>
            <p>A Schoolemanſter would think that a bad Scholler that never turns over the leafe, never gets out of the old into a new leſſon, pardon me if I ſay the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er (though an unparrallel'd one) taught by our Saviour, was taught by him as a maſter (the Law as a Schoole-maſter
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:169877:31"/>not then nulled) Chriſt bids <hi>Peter</hi> not proclaim him the Chriſt (among many reaſons) becauſe he had not by dying and ſatisfying the Law proved himſelf to be the Chriſt;<note place="margin">Compare, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 20. with 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17. <hi>Mat. ver.</hi> 9. — He forbids his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to tell he was <hi>Ieſus Chriſt. ver.</hi> 20. of <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. becauſe he muſt ſuffer death, as <hi>v.</hi> 21.</note> after the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples had been with Chriſt a while and enlightened after by his Spirit (as if in a higher forme) they take out their own leſſons (without conſtruing). I have quoted you <hi>Peters.</hi> I ſhall ſtrive to Pray as the Apoſtles in ſome meaſure by the Spirit, but alſo look back by way of reherſall to repeat the Petitions of the Lords Prayer, he being the Author; while then I admire mens gifts in prayer, and ſtrive to imitate them, let none be diſpleaſed with me concluding all my imperfect prayers, with that moſt abſolute one of my Saviour, ſaying <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi> —</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi> Is the ſpirit as powerfull now as at firſt? <hi>Anſw.</hi> No: Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles and the extraordinary gift of the ſpirit, were as props to ſcaffold up a houſe when to be built, which when once built are taken away;<note place="margin">Impoſitió of hands was uſed in ſetting <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Baruabas</hi> apart to an immediate and particular worke, <hi>Act</hi> 13.2, 3. Who had the ſpirit before; thus we may yet uſe it. <hi>Paul</hi> in the 6 of <hi>Heb.</hi> 1, 2. cals it a principle of Religion; therefore not without danger to be layd aſide.</note> ſo the ſpirits extraordinary power; impoſition of hands was followed by the ſpirit,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169877:31"/>which now we ſadly ſee otherwiſe; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynting with Oyle to cure the ſicke, was once followed by the ſpirit; we have layed aſide the oyle becauſe the ſpirit goes not with it, but impoſition of hands has its uſe.</p>
            <p>Had we the ſpirit as in the Apoſtles time, we might write Epiſtles — as au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentique as theirs (which ſome wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of our age dare affirme) we muſt be content with theirs. Scripture can make perfect (therefore is perfect) no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be added, though our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſay his ſpirit ſhall lead into all truth (by interpreting Scripture, as he did to the Diſciples going to <hi>Emaus</hi>) yet into no new truth, but ſuch as Scripture has, though unknown to many.</p>
            <p>The Scripture is ſomewhat like a roome full of Candles, but not all light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; when new lights are found, as we ſay, they are but truths of Scripture more apparent.</p>
            <p>Hence O Chriſtian thou (having the ſpirit of love and power) maiſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude no finall falling away, as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt and Arminian teach. For how then ſhould Chriſt love to the end, if he
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:169877:32"/>let go his hold, and let thee ſink at laſt? See a few reaſons and proofs for thy future ſtrengthening. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to this purpoſe, what God is to us, and what he promiſes; God is our hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and no finall divorce to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed; no woman (the Churches con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition) has power over her ſelf, no not in this caſe, but the man. No Saint has power to give away himſelfe, for he is not his own but Chriſts; Chriſt is the life, the Saints lives are not in their own power, but hid (feofewed) with Chriſt in God, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.3. As Chriſt is ſafe, ſo is their life; Chriſt is their head; as long as the head's alive, ſo ſhall the members (<hi>ex loco Joh. praecita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> 14.19) the Saints being the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, how were Chriſt perfect or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat if they loſt?</p>
            <p>Yet in this myſticall body the beſt joynts are ſubject unto ſpraines, yea, perhaps to bruiſes and gaſhes, but no bone ſo ſhattered in pieces but may and ſtill is ſet againe. God has promiſed his people eternall life, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.28. They ſhall never periſh. He that gave them is greater then all, and none ſhall pluck them out of his hand, <hi>v.</hi> 9. Nay thoſe that believe (in regard of the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:169877:32"/>of the performance of the promiſe) are ſaid to have eternall life, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 24 He that has once faith to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, ſhall never loſe it, though it may ſeeme loſt for the preſent; for he that is the author of it will be the finiſher, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. The <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega;</hi> if God promiſe ſo, he has ſworn to make it good. God abundantly more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſhew to the heyres of Salvation the immutability of his Counſell, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed it with an Oath, that we might have ſtrong conſolation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.17, 18. <hi>He will confirm you to the end to bee blameleſſe,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.8.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Triplex negatio, vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffimè ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat.</note> I have already quoted his promiſe. <hi>I will never, never, never leave thee</hi> — Heb. 13.5. Indeed the Saints and he being one, 'tis impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble they be ſhould loſt, being part of himſelf. So the Apoſtle is <hi>perſwaded that neither life nor death, nor Angels, princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities nor powers—ſhall be able to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the Saints from the love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord,</hi> Rom. 8.38, 39.</p>
            <p>The will of God is like the Law of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> which alter not,<note place="margin">Du Mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin againſt Armin.</note> or like Pilates <hi>quod ſcripſi ſcripſi</hi> For whom he hath once written in the booke of life he never blots out (there is a difference between the book of life
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:169877:33"/>and living or naturall life; <hi>blot them out of the book of the living — let them not be written among the righteous,</hi> this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall life the Pſalmiſt means, and the world, where the righteous and wicked live together. —)</p>
            <p>Let me examine the grounds of the Apoſtles perſwaſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. Death can't, for in Scripture ſenſe 'tis not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of that name, (though in a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phique ſenſe it may) becauſe it can't ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate a St. from Chriſt; nor is't a curſe, nor puniſhment ſince Chriſt dyed, but a paſſage to him; the hurt of death is taken away, Chriſt has deſtroyed him that has — the power of death, the divel, the executioner; <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14. Where then is death caſheer'd? Why? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſayes one, an Officer that arreſts the Kings ſon, is to be diſcharged of his Office; ſo death for Arreſting Chriſt. The ſting of it by which Satan prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to deſtroy, is blunted, abated, I will not ſay plucked out becauſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in many things we offend all; yet <hi>John</hi> ſayes, <hi>behold the Lambe of God which takes away the ſins of the world;</hi> remember the power of the word<note n="*" place="margin">De medio tollere, <hi>as Budaeus.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> there to take away, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.29.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:169877:33"/>
            <q>
               <l>Quis neget Aeneae magni de ſtripe Neronem?</l>
               <l>Suſtulit hic matrem, ſuſtulit ille Patrem.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Sin in the Saints (Chriſt dying for them —) is much like the Viper on <hi>Pauls</hi> hand, has not a ſting to wound to eternall death;<note place="margin">Chriſt took away the guilt and pniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſinne, and ſactifyes his people much, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing ſin in them <hi>ex Mica ult. antep.</hi>
               </note> to have a Snake in ones boſome with poyſon and teeth out, may as cold water thrown into ones face more ſtartle, feare one, then hurt one. But I forbear, becauſe carnal men, will make a ſport of ſin.</p>
            <p>Though then that counted death continue among us, yet it continues not to be what it was. The name is more terrible then it; think not lying in a grave an argument of the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the power of death, but rather to have all conformable to our Saviour, or to lay aſide corruption in the grave. <hi>Muſculus.</hi> Thy body as now it is, is not capable of immortality, fleſh and blood cannot inherit eternall life; wouldeſt thou bring a corruptible car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſe into heaven to be a glorifyed member of Chriſt? No: then lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide corruption; ſuppoſe it be ſowen in — weakneſſe, it ſhall be raiſed in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Thou foole, that which thou ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt is not quickened except it dye. Keep thy Corne above ground for fear
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169877:34"/>of corruption; where then ſhall the freſh greene blade appeare? When ſhall the ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke grow up? When ſhall it eare? When ſhall it flower? All this glory and advantage will be loſt, if thy Corne be not caſt into the furrows of the earth. Doth not corruption within thee trouble thee more then death? Wert thou not better once dye, then be continually diſquieted with the motions of corruption? Ther's no finall ſubduing them, till the body be deſtroyed, which doth ſo cline and draw thee to thee to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Death to us is bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall, though death thinks to do hurt, as <hi>Phereus la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> enemy was to him he having an Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem in his body, the enemy prickt the Apoſthem and ſo gave him life whom he thought to kill. <hi>Cic. Nat. Deor. Lib.</hi> 3.</note> See if death be not advantage. If a Crab-ſtocke having his head and boughs cut oft, be grafted with a Pip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin or ſome other pleaſant fruit, can it reaſonably complain of hurt? Or has he any wrong done him that has his Cottage of Clay pulled down, and a goodly Pallace of ſtone built for his dwelling? This is thy caſe O beloved. But fooliſh men thinke there is no ſuch life in Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:169877:34"/>
            <p>Let death be fearfull to Heathens, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Some Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers feared it not, but ſaid. <hi>Si mors eſt nos non ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, mors non eſt.</hi>
               </note> and let us not through feare (from which by Chriſts death we are deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>ex Heb.</hi> 2.15.) be any longer ſubject to bondage, L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing in a grave is ſo ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Chriſts lodging there, that that need not trouble a Saint, they like the good ſubject <hi>Ittai</hi> are content to be where their <hi>David</hi> is, in death and life. Chriſt is riſen; ſo muſt his members; he is not here ſayes the Angel, for he is riſen; the Angels Philoſophy proves one body can't be in two places. <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius, Bellarm. enervatus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Death is but a ſleepe; the Nurſe is not afraid to put her Babe to ſleepe; if he ſleepe, he ſhall do well.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our friend</hi> Lazarus <hi>ſleepeth,</hi> Joh. 11. V. 11.<note place="margin">Caldaico-haebraicum &amp; ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat <hi>to lie to ſleepe.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hezekiah</hi> alſo ſlept with his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the grave's aſleeping place, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. thoſe that ſleep expect a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to riſe, we a morning of reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            <p>Neither life — not the many dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers whereby tis in continuall hazard; (for he giveth his Angels charge over his people) not afflictions of this life, for they draw his people neerer, I have ſent ye leanneſſe, cleanneſſe of teeth,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:169877:35"/>want of bread, <hi>but ye have not turned to me ſaith the Lord,</hi> Amos 4.6. Ye ſee God aimed at calling them neerer, not driving them further by affliction. We ought not to ſay depart from us for we are ſinfull men, but draw neere to us— Gods corrections are like <hi>Jonathans</hi> Arrowes to <hi>David,</hi> effects of love, to warn, not deſtroy. Man is apt to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtrue,<note place="margin">Deus uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum habu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it ſilium ſine pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, nullum ſine flagello</note> but God has given us a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary upon his own actions, <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.11. <hi>But I know the thoughts I have to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>they are thoughts of Peace, not of evil;</hi> ſpeaking to his people in caſe of Affliction. The afflictors of the world intend not good to the Saints: But God has the ruling of them; the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> is Gods rod (God keeps (as I may ſo ſpeak) the end of it in his own hand, that the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyrian</hi> ſmite neither deeper nor oftner then he pleaſes) but he thinks not ſo, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 10.4, 7. The horſleech ſucks to fill and ſatisfie itſelfe, but the Phyſitians aym is for good; God out of love cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects his, but will not vouchſafe to correct the wicked, but lets them ripen in ſinne till the day of vengeance, the harveſt. Be not then troubled or caſt down for affliction; remember Saints
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:169877:35"/>are living ſtones (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5.) and to endure; they muſt be like the Sea re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving all waters, and not changing quality, or like <hi>Iob</hi> receiving evil &amp; good patiently; or as a good ſtomach, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive all meats, vomit up none by mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring reluctancy. Of them in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate ſenſe I dare ſay as divine <hi>Seneca</hi> (who is ſaid to have exchang'd Epiſtles with Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) no evils happen to them,<note place="margin">Nihil acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere bono viro mali poteſt. Tot amnes tantum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perne de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> jectorum imbrium non mutant maris ſaporem nec remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunt; it a adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus rerum viri fortis non mutat animum, ſed manet in ſtatu, eſt omnibus externis potentior, ſentitſed vincit, placiduſque contra incurrentia attollitur, adverſa exercitationes pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. Vir erectus labor is eſt appetens honeſti, &amp; ad officia cum periculo promptus. Videmus Athletas cum fortiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis confligere per quos certamini praeparantut; marcet ſine adverſario virtus. Dura non reformidant, nec de fato queruntur, quiequid accidit boni conſulunt, in bonum ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunt, patres mature ad ſtudia obeunda liberos excitari ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent, ſudorem illis, interdum &amp; lachrymas excutiunt, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres ſo vere in ſinu nunquam laborare volunt. <hi>Seneca de provid. cap.</hi> 2.</note> though they feel them and ſmart with them; they change all into good (in theſe being more then conquerours) count all afflictions exerciſes (but not only); vertue they know languiſhes without theſe. Champions ſeeke op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; they that ſtrive for maſterie, deſire to fight, run, wraſtle with others before hand to ſtirre up their ſpirits and encreaſe activity and ſtrength. God ſends his Saints afflictions partly for this end, all working together for good to them that love him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions then (though evil in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) prove good.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:169877:36"/>
            <p>The father ſends his darling to the Schoole of vertue, early to undergo difficulties and learn to pierce obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; 'tis a fond mother ſeeks to keepe them in her boſome idle.</p>
            <p>What honeſt man refuſes labour? Will he not undergo honeſt offices with difficulty and danger? As a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter preach truth though it coſt hot wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? For 'twas once <hi>primus in Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterio &amp; primus in Martyrio.</hi> Sure idleneſſe is painfull to ſome. A good ſoule can as eaſily lack fire and water as Croſſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> praeclara rara.</hi> Heavens joyes are not to be obtained without ſweating.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor life.</hi> If we underſtand the frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of life, becauſe if thou art in Chriſt, they are pardoned. Chriſts death has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled all in heaven and earth; Angels as well as men had benefit of Chriſts death. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 20. Alſo Chriſt's have crucified, or condemned at leaſt,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169877:36"/>
               <hi>the fleſh with its affections and luſts,</hi> Gal. 5.24. They have the ſpirit to conquer with (which is, where ever it be, final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly chiefe maſter, though Satan may live (not only <hi>propè</hi> but <hi>unà</hi>) a while with Chriſt in the ſame houſe, yet there is nor <hi>diviſum imperium;</hi> in the ſame beleever is the houſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> but a kingdom of <hi>David;</hi> Dagon fals at laſt if the Arke be there; though till the laſt combat, the ſpirit appeares not finally victorious. Chriſt thus ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dues ſin in his people and caſts their ſins behind his back, not intending to ſee them, and drownes in them in the depth of the Sea, that they may never float or appeare againſt them, <hi>Micah.</hi> 7.19. Nor Angels nor Principalities; — Principalities and powers are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct offices (if not kinds) of Angels, to whom God commits the managing — of Princedomes — ſo powers may be ſaid to be the Angels, in whom or by whom he manifeſts his power, as Thrones are they in whom as in a Throne (ſayes <hi>Calvin</hi>) Gods Majeſty is declared; now Satan and his aſſume the ſame priviledges (God tolerating, by them to puniſh the diſobedient) but theſe cannot ſeparate — the good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:169877:37"/>will not, the bad cannot, for they are deſtroyed, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.15. See their power and maliceat leaſt curbed. Chriſts death has that efficacy that whomever he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for can never dye, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.34. Who condemneth, ſince Chriſt has dyed? had he dyed for all, application ſhould not have hindred their Salvation; he that gave Chriſt, would freely give all things. Let the divel the accuſer of the brethren climbe up to heaven (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving however his hell with him) and preſent himſelfe for their wrong, they have a friend in Court, Chriſt who is in heaven to appeare for them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.24. Or as <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.34. <hi>who ſitteth at the right hand of God</hi> (that is in equal authority and power) <hi>making inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for us.</hi> Chriſt prayes for us (as I may ſo ſpeake) when we little think of it, ſcarce praying for our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Chriſts prayer is more praeva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then Satans accuſation, or elſe why are not we caſt, Satan ſo often ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing? He deſired to ſift <hi>Peter</hi>—but Chriſts prayer for him, was enough to enable him to ſtand, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.31, 32. His prayer on the Croſſe for his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies (but many of them Elect Veſſels) whoſe ſins till converſion are as many,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169877:37"/>great and haynous (witneſſe <hi>Pauls</hi>) as any (as <hi>Calvin</hi> truly notes) ſo farre prevailed that three thouſand were at <hi>Peters</hi> Sermon converted, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.36.41.3000 men were, ſayes <hi>du Moulin,</hi> then at one Sermon converted; now adayes 3000 Sermons, and not one man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted. But further, Chriſts will is that all that God gave him be with him (where he is) to behold his glory <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. Now, who can reſiſt his will? The good Angels are the executors of his will (having greater power then the loſt Angels) and will with the great aſſiſtant God the Father, ſee the will performed. Now Chriſt has prayed for all that ever ſhal beleeve, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor things preſent.</hi> Not miſeries, not ſin, not Satan, nor the world; <hi>for greater is he that is in you, then he that is in the world,</hi> 1 Joh. 4.4. <hi>&amp;</hi> Joh. 16. laſt. <hi>I have overcome the world.</hi> The Law cannot. Chriſt has fulfilled it. We are not under the Law,<note place="margin">Qui pro nobis ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem vicit, ſemper in nobis vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit — <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
               </note> but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Grace (let the Law be a rule — to ſquare thy actions by, but where thou comeſt ſhort of it, rely on Chriſt, he has performed it for thee) but leaſt of all ſhall feare ſeparate; becauſe the cauſe, ſinne, being removed, the effect cannot. —</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:169877:38"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Not things to come;</hi> as for things to be acted in heaven, the Judge is moſt juſt, nay juſtice it ſelf, and will not, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not wrong <hi>qui videt &amp; novit ut imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alitas &amp; veritas, ſedet ut aequitas—</hi> Bern. <hi>fere in his verbis. Iob</hi> ſpeaks of the things to be acted in heaven with comfort, <hi>I know my Redeemer</hi> (my kinſman ſaies the <hi>Hebrew) liveth,</hi> 19, 26. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Goel</hi> One who redeemeth in the right of a kinſman (a uſuall cuſtome among the Jewes) but remember, O beloved, ſince thus Chriſt redeemed thee, he is to enjoy thee — as for things to be acted on earth, none can (as is ſaid) impriſon any of his without leave, to wit, in the grave, Chriſt having the keyes of the grave — which is but a bed to ſleepe for a time in; I ſhall make my bed in the duſt; ſayes <hi>Iob</hi> 17.13 — where none can be kept without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Chriſt, nor longer then he pleaſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor height;</hi> not the higheſt of men by afflicting; for he (whoſe the Saints are) is higher then the higheſt. Not the height of pride in the Saints, who are kept from the height of pride (as <hi>Paul</hi> was) by the meſſenger of Satan and other continuall humiliations; the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169877:38"/>height of Satans malice and envy is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Gods love to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor depthcannot.</hi> For depth of affliction is anſwered by the height of exaltation; thou bringeſt down to the grave, and bringeſt up again; heavines may endure for a night, but joy comes in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Nor depth of ſin; for as low as one (in Chriſt) can be in ſin, as high he ſhall be in repentance, in grace, in favour; yea though the juſt fall ſeven times in a day, he ſhall riſe again, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.16. Becauſe Chriſt is riſen.</p>
            <p>Hence Satan, ſinne, Hereſie and all that oppoſe, have and do fall down;<note place="margin">Chriſt's may erre, be overta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in an errour, ſeldom an hereſie. <hi>Errare poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, haeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus eſſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu</hi>) but they ſoon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant. Chriſt's are ſons of truth, embrace truth, not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to cloſe with an errour.</note> for Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 2, goes forth conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and thoſe that are ordained to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life ſhall beleeve, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.48. The word being the incorruptible ſeed, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. And being ſowed in the heart, ſhall not finally corrupt or return in vaine, but worke Gods pleaſure by beating down ſinne —</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor any other creature;</hi> for all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the power and Dominion of our mighty Creator and defender, we
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:169877:39"/>are ſure of protection. They can bring upon us,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nec plus ad deſicien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum poteſt terrere pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, quam ad trigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum tutela divina.</hi> Cypr. 'Tis a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for God. The ſpirit of glory and of God reſteth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe who are for Chriſt's ſake reproached, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.14. The very myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Shechinah.</hi>
               </note> but either — <hi>tribulation or diſtreſſe, or perſecution, or famine, or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, or perill or ſword, Rom.</hi> 8.35; and that through leave and Gods ſufferance; <hi>but in theſe we are more then conquerours, through him that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us, ver</hi> 37. For the three children (as we call them) being put into the furnace, behold foure walking looſe. Chriſt was one; who is with his people ſuffering. <hi>Stephen</hi> in the midſt of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, ſees the heavens opened — when the burden ſeemes too great and heavy, Chriſt puts under his ſhoulder to eaſe.</p>
            <p>I remember the ſtory of <hi>Theodore</hi> the Martyr, how when he was wrack't, a young man was ſeen (to the Admiration of al) with a towel to wipe his ſweating limbs, and refreſh him with coole wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſo that he even ſeemed to delight in his miſery. <hi>Ruffin. Eccleſ. Hiſtory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> If nothing can ſeparate the Saints from Chriſt, why doth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſay, <hi>let him that ſtandeth take heed leſt he fall?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 12.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:169877:39"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That Chapter ſpeaks of very ſinfull people (perhaps not elected) though they <hi>were baptized in the ſea</hi> (the outward baptiſme) <hi>and eat of the ſpirituall meat</hi> (though not ſpiritually) for God was not well pleaſed with them, <hi>ver.</hi> 5 but deſtroyed them, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. By effects (if lawfull to judge) theſe men ſhewed themſelves not Chriſt's;<note place="margin">Good men fal into ſin not final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; from Grace, not from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection.</note> had only the outward privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Church, which alone cann't give an aſſurance of perſeverance of Salvation. Theſe might fall away, and ſuch as think they ſtand; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. But <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of unbelief ſuch fall; thou ſtandeſt by Faith, Yet <hi>be not high minded, but feare;</hi> though a filiall feare fears no falling; God by good admonition, (grace co-working) keeps off fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. A caveat to take heed from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, is no infallible proofe of falling; but note, thou ſtandeſt by Faith, thy feet faſt upon the rock Chriſt, if thou continueſt, Gods goodneſſe towards thee, <hi>ver.</hi> 22. As thou maiſt be aſſured thou ſhalt, for Chriſt, as he is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and <hi>Alpha</hi> of thy Faith, will be the finiſher and <hi>Omega.</hi> He confirms to the end to be blameleſſe. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.8.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:169877:40"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> Thoſe whom <hi>Paul</hi> calls Saints, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. he ſayes <hi>may eat and drink damnation,</hi> Chap 11.29. Therefore a falling away of Saints.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> rendred damnation, ought to be rendred by the word judgement; the Apoſtle inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſome among you are ſick, ſome weak (temporal judgements) and ſome aſleep or dead, God bringing that in his anger (not hatred of the Saints, notwithſtanding their ſin) upon his people as a judgement, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed by Chriſts death is none, and yet ſaves the ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob. Heb.</hi> 6.4. One enlightened, that has taſted the good word of God and powers of the world to come, may fall away, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. — Therefore a Saint may fall away, nay fall into the ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Holy Ghoſt, as moſt men thinke, out of that text, that ſin to be included, becauſe tis there, 'tis impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſible to renue them, becauſe they cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie the Son of God afreſh — again, the Apoſtle from <hi>chap.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 26. proves as much, <hi>for if we ſinne</hi> (including himſelf) <hi>wilfully after that we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the knowledge of the truth, there remains no more Sacrifice for ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:169877:40"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I deny not but ſome men may be outwardly baptized (for ſo the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> may be rendred) nay be a hearer with joy (as <hi>Magus</hi> was baptized, <hi>Herod</hi> heard, thoſe in the parable rejoyced, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.13.) yet being not elected or truly ſanctified, fall away.<note place="margin">Vide hiſt. Eccleſiaſt. Magdebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burge. Cent. 4 c. 3. pag. 64. &amp; pag. 89.</note> 
               <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtata had been perchance a practitioner of good in his younger yeares, but at laſt became an enemy to goodneſſe, and concluded his dayes with <hi>viciſti tandem</hi> Galilaee? Thou — haſt overcome at laſt O <hi>Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lean;</hi> in contempt calling Chriſt <hi>Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lean. Anſw.</hi> 2. From that firſt paſſage of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> no falling away can be proved; I mean finall. The words are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is never uſed for fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall falling; 'tis given to the Jewes fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. <hi>v</hi> 11. Yet we expect and pray for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, there is a time of their fulneſſe to come, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ver.</hi> 12. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly blindneſſe is happened but in part to the Jewes, and that only till the fulneſſe of the Gentiles be come in, <hi>ver.</hi> 25. Now <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> does diminiſh the word; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>minuit rem cui adjungi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:169877:41"/>Cornel à lap.</hi> The Jewes falling is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ver.</hi> 12. <hi>hujus cap.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All that can be proved from <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4. is but that Gods people may fall into many ſins and errours, after much knowledge and grace. Neither from this Hypotheſis can it be well conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that they might commit ſuch ſins, falling from ſuch grace; onely the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle —ſhewes a difficulty of reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them, if they did fall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> 'Tis ſaid 'tis impoſſible to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhews it not impoſſible, becauſe the Jewes ſhall be reſtored. I have read the word uſed in a moderate ſenſe; 'tis impoſſible for a rich man to enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven ſayes our Saviour; yet <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> (rich men) are there; it ſhews a difficulty not an impoſſibility.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But theſe <hi>Crucifie Chriſt afreſh,</hi> therefore they are never likely to be renued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Jewes which crucified Chriſt (many) repented and were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; for indeed Chriſt had prayed for them, <hi>Father forgive them, they know
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:169877:41"/>not what they do.</hi> The Apoſtle ſhews the principles of Religion from which theſe are tacitly forbid to fall, and the danger of renewing them ſhewed, <hi>v.</hi> 2. Doctrine of Baptiſme, laying on of hands, and the reſurrection of the dead. The laſt the <hi>Corinthians</hi> denyed, yet being Elected and Saints renewed and ſaved. The other two are denyed in this age, of whom great hope.</p>
            <p>'Tis reported that Witches deny their Baptiſme (ſo that the water ſince receives them not) but ſuch confeſſions ſome of them have made, ſuch repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and have made ſuch ends that I dare not but judge charitably; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore tis not impoſſible to renew ſuch as fall from theſe principles, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently no ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, never mentioned in the Epiſtles, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver called in the Goſpel by that name, but the <hi>Blaſphemy againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> See a book of that Title very judiciouſly pend; and Printed about the year 1646.</p>
            <p>To that of <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 26. I anſwer, tis not ſaid there remains no Sacrifice for their ſin, <hi>there remains no more Sacrifice,</hi> to wit, as in the time of the Law, when for every ſin there was a
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:169877:42"/>Sacrifice; now one only Sacrifice, even Chriſt, the benefit of whom is to be had even by wilfull ſinners, by faith and repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> The word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is to be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred maliciouſly, if we ſin maliciouſly, there remains no Sacrifice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though the word be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſo uſed, as by the <hi>Seventy, Exod,</hi> 21.13, 14. Yet <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> (which under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the <hi>Greek</hi> as well as they) uſes it to ſignifie willingly or wittingly, <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Ethit. cap,</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob. Peter</hi> ſayes, one may deny the Lord that bought them. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 'Tis a prophecy of ſuch as hold univerſall redemption, the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Prophets or Hereticks of which Sect, in their lives deny him whom they falſly taught had redeemed them.</p>
            <p>Saints then perſevere, nothing can ſeparate them from Chriſt; but let not this make us ſecure or negligent, let us walk circumſpectly and carefully, let us work out our Salvation with feare and trembling, that is, the application of it.</p>
            <p>Chriſt has wrought out the Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for us, we muſt endeavour ourſelves to get the aſſurance. <hi>Qui creavit te ſine te, non redimet te ſine te.</hi> This aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169877:42"/>will not be gotten without pains, ſweat, fear, trembling. — Such fear as is accompanyed with joy; ſerve the Lord with fear and rejoyce — <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2. Tremble, thinking on thine own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe and weakneſſe; rejoyce thinking on Chriſts worthineſſe (thine by faith) and Chriſts ſtrength or thine through him; Remember <hi>God has not called us to uncleanneſſe, but holineſſe,</hi> 1 Theſ, 4.7. God as he ordaines to the end ſo he ordaines to the means, which muſt be layed hold on. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> had 15 years added; what more aſſurance needed he then Gods word by the Prophet? Yet he muſt eat and drinke—to preſerve health and uſe a meanes for recovery. <hi>Job</hi> ſayes, man has an appoynted time on earth, and bounds are ſet which he cannot paſſe, yet we muſt uſe lawfull means to live — Chriſt knew the houre of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting out of this world, yet when the Jewes talk of ſtoning him, he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to get out of danger, to teach us. <hi>Paul</hi> knew the Salvation of the Elect to be ſure, yet he is ſaid to endure all things for the Elect, that they may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Salvation (2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.10.) as he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured impriſonment to ſtrengthen
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:169877:43"/>them — and any thing rather then to forbear preaching (to gain them) the means of God unto Salvation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16.</p>
            <p>Let not thoſe who have bound them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves even Apprentiſes to ſin (as I may ſay) and dayly ſerve Satan, think to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any comfort from hence; read <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. <hi>v.</hi> 18, 19. If any man ſhall ſay, <hi>I ſhall have peace though I walk in the imagination of my own heart, adding drunkenneſſe to thirſt; I will not ſpare him</hi> — Doth Chriſt onely love us? Or doth he not alſo beſpeak our love? <hi>O love ye the Lord all ye his Saints,</hi> Pſal. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.23. 'Tis a great honour to be belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of ſuch a perſonage as Chriſt, an honour that he will accept of our love, but more that he ſeeks our love. The honour Saints have by being his, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all honour, <hi>If ye receive honour of men, the honour of God is greater,</hi> Joh. 5. Why do we then court the world and great men for honour; A ſhadow, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; what an honour is it to be a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Chriſt, beſides that of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſity? I read of a <hi>Roman,</hi> that when the Conſulſhip was vacant one day (becauſe of the Conſuls deprival) begg'd it for the few remaining houres,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:169877:43"/>though <hi>cum omnium riſu;</hi>
               <note place="margin">O vigilan tem conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem qui toto ſui conſulatus tempore ſomnum oculis non vidit. <hi>Cicer.</hi> jee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</note> if we ſeriouſly conſider the vanity and unconſtancy of every thing elſe which might ſteal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our love from Chriſt, it might be a means to place it better. Look into the world upon thoſe once lovely Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>Ninive</hi> 66 miles according to Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> and <hi>Babylon</hi> 60 miles, as <hi>Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> reports, <hi>cap.</hi> 69. <hi>Athens</hi> the once glory of Europe (ſo commended and ſet forth by Mr. <hi>Francis Rouſe</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) ruinated. <hi>Sic patet exemplis op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pida poſſe mori.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> above provided by God out of love for his people, is foureſquare, the only ſure foundation. Where are <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha</hi> Cities like unto Paradiſe? That ſweet land, <hi>Canaan,</hi> and the City of God of whom ſo many glorious things are ſpoken I <hi>Jam ſeges eſt ubi Troja fuit—laudant alii claram Rhodon aut Mitylenen— Sed norunt haec monumenta mori</hi> — Where is all thy glory O <hi>Ceſar?</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Parthia eſt caſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſargada nomine, ubi eſt ſepulchrum <hi>Cyri,</hi> &amp; Perſicis litteris hoc Epit aphium, O mortalis, <hi>Cyrus</hi> ego ſum, filius Cambiſae; Aſiae imperavi; Perſarum regnum conſtitui; itaque hoc mihi monumentum non individeas rogo. <hi>Solin. &amp; com. cap.</hi> — 69. —</note> as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther demanded? I read of <hi>Alexander
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:169877:44"/>magnus</hi> his lying many dayes unburyed; of <hi>Cyrus</hi> buryed poorly; <hi>Alexander</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Sepulchre to be opened, did find it true, he found <hi>Duos Scythicos ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, clypeum putrem</hi> — and ſome ſuch poor monuments; <hi>Cuntius Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>Vidimus &amp; magni parva ſepulcra Iovis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where is the old proud <hi>Rome,</hi> the once Miſtriſſe of the Univerſe? which was one of the three things the Father deſired to ſee;<note place="margin">The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts all (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Chriſt and heaven) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Phil. 3.8. i. e. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, dogs meat as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>yes <hi>Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> Chriſt in the fleſh <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam in ſtore</hi> (<hi>Rome</hi> flouriſhing) Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum <hi>in Ore</hi> (<hi>Paul</hi> Preaching) its glory is only now to be ſeen in the duſt. The Prophet cals to us, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 55.1, 2. <hi>Wherfore do ye lay out money for that which is not bread, and your labour for that which ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfyeth not,</hi> or laſteth? It ſatisfies not; for the world is round, and the heart three-cornered; the round world can't content the three cornered heart; the three perſons of the Trinity only can; a ſpirit can only ſatisfie a ſpirit, God that made it, and his love can only pleaſe it; <hi>Domine, tu feciſti nos, &amp; irrequietum eſt cor noſtrum donec in te quieſcat</hi> Laſteth not; conſtant in unconſtancy onely. Earth's pleaſures are like the Apples which grew by <hi>Sodom,</hi> very pleaſant and beautifull to look upon, but touch
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:169877:44"/>them and they moulder into duſt or nothing. <hi>Solin Polyhiſt. cap.</hi> 48. Love Chriſt then, thou ſeeſt all things come to an end, <hi>but the commandements— are exceeding broad,</hi> Pſal. 119. ver. 96. Man of late growes much in love with Souldiery or butchery, as if it were a vertue to kill thoſe for whom Chriſt dyed? If<note n="*" place="margin">Si fas coedindo coeleſtia ſcandere cuiquam— M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſoli coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li maxima potta pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet. Enni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us de Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cano.</note> killing of Chriſtians and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers be to love Chriſt, why ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons he <hi>Paul,</hi> with a <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me?</hi> Act. 9.4. If they not ſlaine as profeſſors of Chriſt, yet in fine profeſſors of Chriſt ſlain.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Solomon</hi> a type Chriſt ſignifies peace, Chriſt came to reconcile wrath, to prevent death,— and as he was the Prince of Peace, ſo he came when the world was at peace moſt, in <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Reign.</note> Chriſt is the only true object of love. Doſt love preferment? Thou ſhalt be by him made the ſonne of God; <hi>David</hi> thought it much to be ſon in Law to a King, though an earthly and wicked one; thou ſhalt be an heyre; for every ſon is an heyre, <hi>Gal</hi> 47. A ſtrange thing, and that to an incorruptible inheritance. Doſt love freedome, that ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by all, for which ſo much blood ſhed? (that which being gained once and pronounced aloud, the people made ſuch acclamations and filled the ayre with ſhouting, that birds fell down dead becauſe of the rarefacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ayre, or vertiginouſneſſe and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:169877:45"/>aſtoniſhment, as <hi>Plutarch in mag. Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peio &amp; in Flaminio</hi>) by Chriſt thou ſhalt be free from the tyranny of ſin and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan (a choyce freedome) and art a free Deniſon of heaven. Doſt love pleaſure? <hi>with him are pleaſures for evermore.</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt love riches? <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> (the effect of Chriſts love) <hi>is great riches,</hi> 1 Tim. <hi>c. ult. ver. 8. a treaſure laid up in heaven, where the theif cannot break through and ſteale.</hi> Doeſt love travels? thou ſhalt by loving him travel from earth to heaven, ſee that ſo coveted ſight, the true holy land, and though not the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, yet Chriſt raiſed from the dead. Doeſt deſire to heare muſick? that which ſo quickned <hi>Davids</hi> ſpirit, (notwithſtanding he had the ſpirit in a moſt plentiful manner for man on earth;) in heaven (purchaſed by Chriſt through love) are Harps and muſick (to ſpeak to capacity) to pleaſe—<hi>Revel.</hi> 5.8, 9.—there Harpers ſing a new ſong. I wonder, if muſick ſinful, why in the time of the Law commanded? God never commanded any thing that was a ſin; not wearing long haire, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Nazarites—<hi>Eliſha,</hi> (ſayes <hi>Rabbi Da. Kimchi</hi> upon 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.15.) cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for a Timbrel to diſpel his grief, for
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:169877:45"/>the loſſe of <hi>Elijah,</hi> or to compoſe his ſpirits much moved with indignation at <hi>Jehoram;</hi> ſee Muſique uſed by the Prophet to diſpel ſorrow, or to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his ſpirits—notwithſtanding his having the ſpirit; if it had been ſinful, God would not have ſet forth the joys of heaven by it.</p>
            <p>If we conſider Chriſts love in under-going the burden of our ſin (it may be a motive to us to love him) Chriſt ſunk under their heavie weight, he<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>julavit, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay 53.</hi> u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> grave quoddam onus p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri ſolet. Gerh in harm. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vang.</note> bore our iniquities as an heavie load—hence make this uſe, if thine iniquities are an heavie burden (a good ſigne, if felt) remember Chriſts condition—ſay to him <hi>(who was like to us in all things ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cept ſin)</hi> as the Pſalmiſt—<hi>pardon my ſin for it is Wondrous great,</hi> Pſal. 25.11. we may acquaint him with our condition, our miſery the occaſion of his mercy; heavineſſe of our ſin, the occaſion of his ſudden eaſing us. —</p>
            <p>Conſider his love in dying<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Propriè in humeros tollere ad geſt indum quaſt leve. Mr. Leigh in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hum.</hi> Chriſt fell upon his face, ſome ſay through weakne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> carry his croſſe quire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long; <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renaeus</hi> helped. Compare the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels.—</note> 
               <hi>greater love then this has no man, that one ſhould lay down his life for his friends</hi> (ſo calle, in reſpect of election and Chriſts deat foreſeen, and conſequently reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) nature at his death put on mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing apparel, the earth trembled to bear
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:169877:46"/>a dying Saviour, the rocks rent becauſe mans heart was ſo hard; and a ſtranger to <hi>Iſrael</hi> cryed out ſeeing ſuch an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clips, <hi>Vel Deus naturae patitur, vel hic mundus diſſolvitur.</hi> So much Chriſt by dying has done for his, that no Latine word can expreſſe his ſalvation <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>uno vocabulo Latino non poteſt exprimi,</hi> ſayes <hi>Tully, fere his verbis. Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vator</hi> comes ſhort of it; Chriſt may be ſaid to be <hi>Servator daemonum</hi>—as preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them from relapſing to nothing; <hi>Salvator</hi> doth not expreſſe it; he was <hi>Salvator angelorum,</hi> keeping them ſafe from fall; but reſtored man to all loſt priviledges and farre better; <hi>foelix la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pſus qui talem meruit Servatorem.</hi> Some would have the Greek rendred by <hi>Soſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tator; ſoſpitantur enim ea quaefuerunt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita.</hi> Laurent in 2 Pet, 1.1. <hi>Servantur vero &amp; ſalvantur ea quaenon fuerunt perdi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a.</hi> But <hi>Antigonus,</hi> for liberty reſtored to the Lacedemonians, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Were we loſt in <hi>Adam?</hi> and are we not found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt? we were ſons by creation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o are the wicked, even <hi>Dives:</hi> heires we were of an earthly Paradiſe, not comparable in any thing to Heaven; we had life, ſhould have never died — <hi>mors à morſu</hi> — But by Chriſt we are
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:169877:46"/>ſons of God adopted; more are we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding for being reſtored to immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties once loſt, then the Angels that were only preſerved from fall; <hi>magis gratis datur,</hi> ſays <hi>Aqui.</hi> Chriſt left the 99 (good Angels) to ſeek man that was loſt (as well as the 99. Proud Phariſees— who ſeem and think to need no Saviour (but ſome temporal deliverer) no repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance;) by Chriſt we are heirs of that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe of which <hi>Adam's</hi> but a Type, and have eternal life through death; <hi>Adam</hi> (though great Clerks are againſt it) ſhould never have died, not been hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py and glorious, but through ſin and Chriſt; yet with the phites we worſhip not the Serpent, but God who brought good out of evill. <hi>Queſtion,</hi> Why then was heaven made before the fall? <hi>Solu.</hi> Becauſe God foreſaw it, Should all men have lived on earth for ever, and ſtill begat children, the world could not have contained them; which God foreknew — let Chriſt be only our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; let us have neither other ſaviours, interceſſours, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: the Pope has he ſaies the over-plus of other Saints good works to diſpoſe of; thus the Saints (in that opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo derogatory from Chriſt) ſave themſelves and others; but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:169877:47"/>the good Angels and Saints have (as wiſe Virgins, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.) little oyle enough for themſelves, (God can charge his Angels &amp; Saints with folly.)</p>
            <p>The Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> had ſin (as <hi>Scotus</hi> proved) for ſhe rejoyced in a Saviour, the Apoſtles were bid to ſay <hi>forgive us our treſpaſſes</hi>— and thoſe that will not, God forgive them; now where ſin is, there no merits are (ſaies judicious <hi>Calvin.</hi>) <hi>Peter</hi> ſinned after Chriſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for him (thus the Pope his ſucceſſor) not only in denying his Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, but continually— the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of ſinners, affirms him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf cheif, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15. and adviſes the Saints inſtead of cenſuring others, and preferring themſelves, to think better, or eſteeme other better then themſelvs, 2 <hi>Phil. ver.</hi> 3. Corne, the richer in the eare, the more it hangs the head; the more a man is in Chriſt, the more ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible he is of his natural miſery—and the more humble—pray only to Chriſt; we have one only Mediator, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. and know and acknowledge no other Interceſſor (unleſſe prayers of Saints on earth, ſo underſtand <hi>Job</hi> 5.) for I am perſwaded for particulars, <hi>Abraham knowes us not, and Iſrael is ignorant of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:169877:47"/>us</hi> (I ſay 63.16. and know not our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular wants—) but thou O Lord art our Redeemer; give not his glory to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, God is a jealous God.</p>
            <p>Chriſt ſaves; wo to them that imitate the Devil in ſtriving to deſtroy and to make men ſin; if ſuch out of love, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and Chriſts example will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare: yet let me deſire them to be as charitable to themſelves and others, as <hi>Dives; I have five brethren</hi> (to omit that explanation of <hi>Moſes</hi> 5 Books —) <hi>ſend to them leſt they come to this place of torment,</hi> ſaies he; what charity in hel? <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas</hi> tels us there be no good thoghts there (for they were to no purpoſe) but whether a parable or no, thus much ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Dives</hi> knew his bad example and life—had made his brethren ſin, and therefore concluded he ſhould have the greater damnation; to prevent which he would have them by <hi>Lazarus</hi> admoniſhed. <hi>Go and do likewiſe.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but blood could redeem. I doubt me <hi>Zipporah</hi> ſpake more out of paſſion then faith, when ſhe ſaid, thou art an husband of blood, to <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 4.25. yet it may thus be rendred, <hi>thou art a huſband to me preſerved by blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Creation to this was an eaſie work; <hi>dictum &amp; factum,</hi> the firſt; but
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:169877:48"/>the ſecond coſt Chriſts hearts blood. Chriſt was maſtred and over<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome by ſinful men; he wraſtled with <hi>Jacob,</hi> and was overcome to prelude to his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being then as man prevailed over; conſider his willingneſſe, <hi>I lay down my life,</hi> yet the occaſion ours; <hi>nihil iſte— nec potuit—mea fraus</hi>— conſider the deformity of ſin, how did Chriſt look (appearing cloathed with ſin, deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of mankind) before divine juſtice. God even abſents himſelf from him, ſcarce acknowledging him; it was his love to lie in a grave (to ſweeten it to his people) two dayes part of the third; the Sabbath was a Type of it (together with reſting from ſin, and eternall reſt) now 'tis the Lords day in memorial of his glorious<note n="*" place="margin">On the Lords day our firſt day of the week, five things we read done only as the work of the day; 1. Being in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit or ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. 2. Preaching <hi>ex</hi> 20. <hi>Actorum.</hi> Adde in the third place prayer. 4 Breaking Bread or Sacraments. 5. Diſtribution to the Saints; the Apoſtle ordained or commanded thus the Church of <hi>Gal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ia.</hi> Dr. <hi>Prideaux.</hi> To worſhip—(being the Moral part of the command, is kept.)</note> Reſurrection and Aſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; let no man therefore judge you in reſpect of holy dayes (the Iewiſh eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally) or the new Moon or the Sabbath, being ſhadows, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.16.17. conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his love unto man in giving him his reward (out of mercy, not merit;) As
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:169877:48"/>ſoon as dead, <hi>thou ſhalt be with me this day in Paradiſe, Luke</hi> 23.43. and <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> dyed, and was immediately carried by the Angels to <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, that is heaven, (where note, ſince Chriſts death, the glory of the Saints is greater then before, but no <hi>Limbus;</hi> Chriſt aſcen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding no doubt gave ſome more honour to the Saints in heaven as well as his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit on earth; the head is more honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then the boſome; the glory of the S<hi rend="sup">ts</hi> before Chriſts death, was expreſſed by being received into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſom, now being gathered to Chriſt the head) and <hi>Dives</hi> dying was in hell in torment, though a Parable,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 16.22, 23.</note> yet <hi>Keck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erman</hi> hence fetches his greateſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prove a fire in hell; why not I to prove the gluttons immediate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there after death? hence know there is a particular judgment immediately after the ſouls departure (as well as a general at laſt) as 'tis appointed for man once to die, <hi>ſo after death comes judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (Heb. 2.27.) <hi>viz.</hi> particular— elſe how could <hi>Dives</hi> be in hell, except this private judgement paſſed; the juſt judge does not as the memorated judge of the Stannery's in <hi>Devon,</hi> who hanged a man in the forenoon, and ſate in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:169877:49"/>after; there is a general aſize to be hereafter, to condemne the wicked, but to acquit the righteous; the wicked Angels alſo are in torment before the great day, being in chains, reſtrained, in darkneſſe and as <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> ſuffering (not to ſuffer) the paines of eternal fire, <hi>Iude</hi> 6.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> If Chriſt's are in glory imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after death, did he not wrong them to returne them to the body, in raiſing them up—?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It was heaven to them to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God by their raiſing. <hi>Paul</hi> (though in the third heaven) moſt contented to glorifie Chriſt on earth.<note place="margin">Perchance they were ſaid to be dead, and the ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tt to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve ſo.</note> 2. <hi>Anſw.</hi> No mention being made by <hi>Lazarus</hi> or any of them of heaven (but <hi>Paul</hi> who was there before death—) I rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive they were not in joy — but God miraculouſly (ſure much beyond na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) kept the ſoule in ſome traunce as it were, or extacy to glorifie Chriſt, and ſhew his power in quickning the body— from which the ſoule not departed, but ſlept, <hi>ſhe is not dead, but ſleepeth</hi>— ſayes our Saviour; <hi>the ſickneſſe is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death, but unto the glory of God</hi> — ſpeaking of <hi>Lazarus;</hi> perchance had their time (as we ſay) beene come, it
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:169877:49"/>had been otherwiſe. I hope I wrong not Chriſts miracles, or come neer the errour of ſoul-ſeekers.</p>
            <p>But to returne to Chriſts love, he loves the father and the children; ſee the continuance of it.<note place="margin">If a belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to have his child bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed (in whom ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe no vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible grace) it ought not to be refuſed baptiſme; know, God hears deſires, and looks on a willing mind (ſigns of grace) conſidering eſpecially the promiſe to beleevers children, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.13, 14 <hi>Acts</hi> 3.25. &amp; 2.39. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.17.</note> I wonder why the <hi>Antipoedobaptists</hi> wrong their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and curtaile the promiſe, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning Chriſts love only in the Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; 'tis not the nature of grace, or this Sacrament, to finde or look for a prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition, the Parents deſire ſufficeth.</p>
            <p>Pardon the digreſſion, if I uſe a word or two to ſet forth Gods love in the promiſe, and its freeneſſe; but firſt take it from <hi>Origine</hi> (who lived but 200 yeers after Chriſt) that Baptiſme of infants was received by the Church from the very Apoſtles, declared in <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. and <hi>Auguſtines</hi> fourth Book againſt the Donatiſts, <hi>cap.</hi> 24. affirmes Baptiſme of Infants not to be by mans authority, no nor counſels, but the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles doctrine. <hi>Peter</hi> tels the Jewes, <hi>the Promiſe is made to them and to their
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:169877:50"/>children,</hi> Acts 2.39. the anſwer of the Antipaedobaptiſt is, if the children do beleeve; but let us conſider well and we ſhall find the text to be otherwiſe meant. God promiſed <hi>Abraham</hi> to be a God to him and of his ſeed, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands him Circumciſion, and his ſeed at eight dayes old, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. <hi>Peter</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Jewes, repeats the ſubſtance of the Promiſe, affirming Chriſt would be ſo to them beleeving, and to all afar off beleeving, and to their ſeed by vertue of the Promiſe. God promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to Iſrael his ſpirit (and conſequently himſelf to be Iſraels God) <hi>and to his ſeed and ſeeds ſeed,</hi> Eſay 59. <hi>ult.</hi> Iſraels chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were Circumciſed; and are not we Gentiles the ſpiritual ſeed of <hi>Abraham?</hi> are not our children capable of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe too? does not <hi>Peter</hi> ſo repeat the tenure of the Covenant, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.2. <hi>ult. yee</hi> (ſpeaking to the Jewes) <hi>are the children of the Covenant</hi> firſt; what means that word <hi>firſt,</hi> if the Covenant belong'd not to us Gentiles ſecondly? the Apoſtle was loth to ſay the Covenant in the ſecond place did belong to us Gentiles (whom they hated) leaſt it might keep them off—<hi>Paul</hi> after, but ſaying he would turne to the Gentiles,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:169877:50"/>ſaw their rage, when they ſaid, away with ſuch a fellow from the earth; but remember he joynes Circumciſion and Baptiſme together, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11, 12. but <hi>yee are circumciſed—being buried with Chriſt in Baptiſme, Num, jung antur jam Gryphes equis?</hi> it ſeems Baptiſm &amp; Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion may ſtand almoſt in the ſame verſe, as if they might have ſome affini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or acquaintance; as if <hi>Paul</hi> would have ſaid, ye being baptized, are in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant as thoſe circumciſed.—Could <hi>Moſes</hi> give a greater priviledge then Chriſt? Could he afford children Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, and not Chriſt Baptiſme? Suppoſe a Landlord make a Leaſe to a man and his heirs—then recall that, and make or give it to the man and not his heirs, which is the greateſt privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge? the firſt that's <hi>Moſes;</hi> to the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and their ſeed, freely; the ſecond is Chriſt's, to the beleever, not his ſeed, or heir, unleſſe he have ſome ability to hold the farme (as I may ſay) eaſed—according to the Antipaedobaptiſt. But you'l ſay, 'tis no priviledge for the child to be baptiſed and in Covenant by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the father not having faith. I wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly omit that tis in the world a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge to be a Gentleman by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:169877:51"/>though the ſon have not that ſtock of riches; but why may not they be ſaid to have faith? is it becauſe actual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they expreſſe it not? then neither may they be accounted reaſonable; ſure Children have had grace, <hi>Iohn</hi> &amp; Chriſt the ſpirit from the womb,<note place="margin">We read not that either in <hi>John</hi> or Chriſt grace and the ſpirit much ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared when chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, yet ſanctified from the womb. <hi>Johns</hi> grace, as himſelfe, ſeemed to be in the deſert till the time of his ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt had a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ient for a time. <hi>John</hi> expreſſed his having the ſpirit once, when in the womb he leaped.—</note> ſo that Chriſt (though he be ſaid to encreaſe in wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſtature &amp; favour with God &amp; man, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. <hi>ult.</hi>) increaſed not in wiſdome (but in appearance of men, and ſo in favour with God and really with men) only in the exerciſe of it, having the ſpirit at firſt in a plentiful manner; but theſe examples are extraordinary; but did not Chriſt bleſſe the children, and conſequently give them grace? deny not Baptiſm to known grace? yet you'l ſay he baptiſed them not; how is it known but his Diſciples did? they were brought by friends; was not here the forenamed deſire? perchance faith; he that gave the greater, the bleſſing, will he deny the leſſe, Baptiſme? <hi>to theſe belongs the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> ſayes Chriſt. What Kingdom that of grace, deny not Baptiſme to viſible grace; if
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:169877:51"/>that of glory, much leſſe deny it, <hi>Calv.</hi> Were not all the fathers and children baptized to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Cloud (out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly?) and eat of the ſpiritual meat, but not ſpiritually? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2.3. If you ſay Chriſt bid go and teach and baptize—therefore teaching goes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore—I anſwer, as the Jewes, <hi>non da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri prius &amp; poſterius in Scripturis,</hi> the Scripture looks more at the ſubſtance then order — but when 'tis ſaid <hi>repent and beleeve,</hi> ſure faith ſhould be firſt. Chriſts words were moſt fit for thoſe times, when ancient people were moſt to be dealt with, who were firſt to be taught — then baptized; but their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren might (begotten after Baptiſme, eſpecially) be baptized firſt — Baptiſm &amp; teaching are the two duties belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a Miniſter, which that place more aimed at then the order.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. ſayes, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are holy; federally I ſay, matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nially ſay the Antipaedobaptiſts; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the Corinthians needed not to be inſtructed or taught that their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were holy in marriage, that is, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimate, or not baſtards, though both parents were unbeleevers for marriage was before Chriſt; but it ſeemed (ſince
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:169877:52"/>Iſrael was commanded (and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Corinthians) not to marry with unbeleevers, theſe doubted whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two might live together; of whom one ſince marriage, was converted, the other remaining in unbelief—the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle reſolves they might, firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the beleeving perſon (by Gods bleſſing) might gain the other: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, becauſe their children (by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of one parents beleeving) were ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and conſequently admittable by Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſme into the viſible Church.</p>
            <p>Let us continue the memorial of Chriſt's continued love in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper, becauſe Chriſt commanded us ſo to do, becauſe every Ordinance of Chriſt is very profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table; becauſe to the people of God means of more grace; ſee the <hi>Directory</hi> about the Lords Supper: This may in ſome meaſure be gathered from the Symbols of Bread and Wine (made choyce of by our Saviour) nouriſhing, cheriſhing, ſtrengthning elements; had the Sacrament been only to confirme, why then commanded to be uſed of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten? once might have ſufficed, as <hi>Keck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erman</hi> ſayes of Juſtification, <hi>eſt actus ſemel in vitâ adhibitus,</hi> or to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe;
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:169877:52"/>if Sacraments only ſeal, once ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſtired were enough; a Seal fixed once ſufficeth, where the Teſtator alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not his Will; now God changeth not. Moſt call the Sacrament the ſouls food, therefore muſt nouriſh, but not <hi>ex opere operato;</hi> let all members of the body of Chriſt, the Church partake, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving knowledge to examine themſelvs; Let dogs in the Goſpel ſenſe be exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>without are dogs; nil aliud fuit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus mundus ante converſionem niſi hara porcorum aut colluvies rabidorum ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi> Aug. Doth he then allow his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple all uſeful means for their ſouls, who denyes them this? let the Saints judge.</p>
            <p>As an Appendix; Chriſt being at meat uſed the poſture of lying (upon a bed) when he inſtituted his Supper, not ſitting, though we tranſlate the word according to our cuſtome: when we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, we uſe private ejaculations, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore kneeling becomes us, conſidering alſo what a benefit we hope to receive: the moſt humble way were not amiſſe:<note place="margin">The words <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhew as much.</note> What if the Diſciples did ſit (as we tranſlate the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) with our Saviour at meat before his death? yet more reverence was expected after he was riſen; he in heaven, we on earth, he
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:169877:53"/>a King, we his ſubjects; we miſerable, he perfectly glorious: <hi>Mary Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> may not be equally familiar after his reſurrection as before; 'tis now, <hi>touch me not, John</hi> 20.17. yet before ſhe waſhed his feet and wiped them—</p>
            <p>Since beleevers are Chriſts beloved,<note place="margin">Vſes.</note> they are ſure of protection, being the apple of his eye, <hi>Zach</hi> 2.8, his Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17. His anoynted ones, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 105.15. none of which may be touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. In this life they are ſafegarded, in time of death, by the power of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Angels who immediately carry the ſoul triumphing through Chriſt to heaven; after death care is taken of the duſt and aſhes, for the Angels which gather the elect from the four corners of the earth, care for them, and gather (ſayes <hi>Coll. Conimb.</hi>) the duſt of his people together, out of which God ſhall reſtore the body (as the Phenix) but not weak as before, but powerful, immortal, glorious.</p>
            <p>God, all know, took care of the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral Temple, a Type of Chriſt's real body, and myſtical, the Church; the Saints are a ſpiritual Temple to him, he will then take care of them; <hi>If any man deſtroy or defile the Temple of God, him
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:169877:53"/>will God deſtroy; for the Temple of God is holy, which Temple are yee,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.17. Iſrael through Chriſt, <hi>is holineſſe to the Lord:</hi> he that ſhall devoure him (or any true beleever) <hi>evill ſhall betide him</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.3. ſince God has anoynted his people with the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Chriſt, he promiſes to take off the yoke of bondage, <hi>Eſay</hi> 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 27. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the anoynting. So careful of theſe is Chriſt, that he raiſes up ſtrangers to ſafegard them ſometimes. <hi>Let mine out-caſts dwell with thee O Moab, be thou a cover to them from the face of the ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> Eſa. 16.4. ſometimes natives, even their brethren, in the midſt of trouble, as 1 <hi>Kings.</hi> 18.4. <hi>Obadiah,</hi> maugre <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habs</hi> malice againſt them, took an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of the Lords Prophets, and hid them and fed them. <hi>Eliakim</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a naile faſtned to the wall or ſure place, on which all the veſſels of the Sanctuary, ſmall &amp; great, from thoſe of cups, to thoſe of flagons ſhould be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like hung, and by him ſupported:<note place="margin">Eſa. 22.24.</note> where obſerve, the Saints compared to veſſels, the weak to ſmall veſſels; the ſtrong to greater, but all to be ſupported.</p>
            <p>Suffer then Gods people in matter of opinion or judgement,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 2.</note> till God ſhall
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:169877:54"/>reveale<note place="margin">Yet rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate men for a time may erre in points fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did about Chriſts kingly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, <hi>Act</hi> 1. the Gala<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tians about juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But as they do not eaſily erre thus, ſo being convinced they ſoon recant.</note>—<hi>Phil.</hi> 3.15. The rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they hold the ſame fundamentals, the ſame Chriſt. Errours not holding the head, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.19 and damnable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, would quickly un<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Saint a man. Opinions of Saints (if otherwiſe erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous) cannot damne. They be <hi>wood, hay, ſtubble</hi> indeed, which the fire or operation of the Spirit burns up in a triall; but their ſoules ſhall be <hi>ſaved by fire,</hi> to wit, their underſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enlightened, and conſcience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed by the light of the truth as fire, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.15. Forbeare not to preach matters of duty and truth: if any by it be offended, remember 'tis better pleaſe God then men. In this <hi>Paul</hi> did not forbeare <hi>Peter</hi> one jota, but withſtood him face to face, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.11. Suffer the Saints in matters of liberty, as eating <hi>fleſh or herbs,</hi> 1 Gor 8. alſo uſe no other coercive meanes but the Word; for God promiſes never a bleſſing to the ſword, unleſſe that of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pirit, to gain a member out of a dangerous opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Nor can the Magiſtrates ſword prevaile over a Spirit, as is the ſoule and that act of it the <hi>underſtanding,</hi> to reform or inform it. If in the time of the Law other coercive power then the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:169877:54"/>Word was uſed (which that paſſage of <hi>Joſiah</hi> proves not, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.33. for he compelled the people to ſerve God, by reading, or cauſing the Law to be read to them, <hi>ver.</hi> 30.) yet the time of the Law differed from this of the Goſpel. <hi>Elijah</hi> then may call for fire from heaven to deſtroy: — but <hi>John</hi> and <hi>James</hi> muſt not; our Saviour tels them they are of another ſpirit, <hi>Luk</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 35. 'Twere to deny Chriſt come in the fleſh, to hold forth the Law, and uſe the ſcepter, which was but to laſt till <hi>Shilo</hi> came. <hi>Compell,</hi> as in <hi>Luk.</hi> 14.23. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by powerfull perſwaſion, by ſhewing the neceſſity of believing, as that word may be rendred. 'Twere needleſſe uſing any other meanes then the Goſpel,<note place="margin">A ſhepherd may uſe better meanes to bring home a wandring ſheep, then by worry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to death.</note> that being <hi>the very power of God to ſalvation,</hi> Rom. 1. <hi>Fides non cogenda. Natura hominis ducitur, non cogitur. Suſpendite verbera, oſtendite ubera. Non Chriſtiani ad crucem, ſed ad lucem; errantes opinione gladio male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicto ne corrigas, ſed veritate dirigas.</hi> Let Gods people be enlightned, not frightened. <hi>Quod verbum non man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davit, veritas damnavit, Chriſtus non approbavit, peccatorem non curabit.</hi> What the Word commands not, to
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:169877:55"/>Gods people commend not: What medicine Chriſt doth not ſend, thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm people will never mend.</p>
            <p>What ſhall be done to damnable ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing Hereticks?<note place="margin">Quaeſt.</note> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Let the Church after due admonition reject, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.11. Let the Magiſtrate reſtrain: ſuffer not a man with a running ſore to go abroad to infect. One way to put out the fire in an oven, is to ſhut it up. Hereſie is not onely of a depraved un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: (the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to take up (as it were willingly) he latter part of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> alſo ſhewes as much; Words ending in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhew a quality and a delight taken in it; But if it were, that Mountebank who out of miſtake ſells poyſon for phyſick, ought not to be licenſed to practiſe. <hi>Thou ſuffereſt that woman Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſabel,</hi> was a fault objected to the Church <hi>Rev</hi> 2.20. and <hi>haſt thoſe that hold</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) and ſtiffly maintain <hi>the Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laitans doctrine, which thing</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>I hate,</hi> to wit, your ſufferance of ſuch, <hi>v.</hi> 15. An heretique ſinnes after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing, <hi>ex.</hi> Tit. 3.11. againſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; for he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of himſelf; In pertinacia perſeverans,</hi> Erring fundamentally (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) he
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:169877:55"/>is ſaid to be ſubverted <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Church-fundamentals topſie torvè upſide down, or as a ſhip whoſe keel is above the water. <hi>Peter</hi> parallels the ſinne of ſuch an Heretick with the falſe Prophets, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. who was to die, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.5, 9 We ought to be more carefull of mens ſoules, then lives.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh ſtrive for the faith once delivered to the Saints</hi> That is the true ſhield,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3.</note> which if preſerved, all is well.</p>
            <q>
               <l>— The wounded Theban cry'd,</l>
               <l>How fares my ſhield? Which ſafe, be ſmil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d and dy'd.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Let not the bleating of <hi>Jeroboam's</hi> Calves entice thee from the Temple. Opinions are (ſayes L. <hi>Verulam</hi>) as the ſtrivings of one <hi>Iſraelite</hi> with another, which <hi>Moſes</hi> fairly compoſes but He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies are as the <hi>Egyptians</hi> ſtriving with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which <hi>Moſes</hi> knocks down.—But I return.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Hom.</note> Miniſters are ſhepherds, and ſhould not only have a rod, but muſt provide paſture for the ſheep. Kings are ſo too, and muſt protect and provide folds, and take care of the poor, ſick, weak flock of Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:169877:56"/>
            <p>God finds fault that the weak and diſeaſed were puſhed away with horns,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe <hi>4.</hi> Information.</note> that is, by power, <hi>Ezek</hi> 34.21. When the <hi>whore</hi> in <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.5. is judged, both ſmall and great Saints rejoyce. <hi>Love</hi> them who glorifie Chriſt: remember, God rewards and bleſſes them who protect his people. <hi>Cyrus</hi> his ſhepherd, in the quoted ſenſe, or alluſion had to his education, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 44. <hi>v. ult.</hi> and his <hi>annointed,</hi> c. 45.1. becauſe he took as much care of Iſrael as if he had been their King, chiefly, proſpers much: for indeed God advanced him for their ſake, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. though in his male iſſue he continued not to a grandchild, yet in <hi>Atoſſa</hi> his daughter,<note place="margin">One being <hi>Cyrus</hi> his daughter, the other <hi>Morde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'s</hi> uncles. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 7.</note> wife to <hi>Darius Hiſtaſpis</hi> (not <hi>Hadaſſah</hi> or <hi>Heſter</hi>) his race continued. And to make the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence the more remarkable, (ſayes Mr. <hi>Goodwyn</hi>) whereas <hi>Darius</hi> had ſons by another wife, yet the Intereſt of <hi>Atoſſa,</hi> for <hi>Cyrus</hi> ſake, carried the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to <hi>Zerxes</hi> her ſon, <hi>Cyrus</hi> grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>child; and the laſt <hi>Darius</hi> with whom the Empire was deſtroyed, was of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other race Such regard had God to <hi>Cyrus</hi> his ſhepherd and his ſeed, that favoured the Jewes. Gods people are bleſſing in the midſt of the land where
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:169877:56"/>they are well entertained, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 19.24. The new wine in the grape, is the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t one ſayes, Deſtroy it not. So are Gods people a bleſſing where they are, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. Read the elegant expreſſion of <hi>Zach.</hi> 1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>. to the 7. <hi>ver.</hi> to this purpoſe. The abuſing Gods people, is the occaſion of a curſe — The Kings rove up and down freely, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. till <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot</hi> Gods anointed is tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched: he is Gods coyn, bears his ſtamp, grace; ſince they borrow him, they muſt repay with uſury, paying their lives for the loan. The Church is Chriſts firſt born, (all heires) Remember, all <hi>Egypts</hi> firſt-born ſlain, for oppoſition made to their freedome. 'Twere able to make one ſad, melancholy, and dejected, ſeriouſly to conſider that nights miſery: <q>Horrida, ſquallida, lurida, tetrica,<note place="margin">Herman. Hugo.</note> terribilis Nox.</q>
Not one houſe, in which not one (and that the firſt-borne) dead: But that 'twas Gods juſt judgment upon his and his beloved's enemies. This, and their overthrow in the Red ſea, was ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, that we heare no more of that Nation, till the dayes of <hi>Solomon.</hi> — Read but <hi>Edom's</hi> rejoycing at Gods peoples captivity, in <hi>Obad.</hi> the Prophet,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:169877:57"/>
               <hi>v.</hi> 8.11, 12. and Gods anger with them for it, and you'll be confirmed in the concluſion, That God bleſſes thoſe that bleſſe his people, and curſes thoſe that curſe them,<note place="margin">Signes of love, &amp;c.</note> or laugh at their calamity. And will he not at laſt put the ſcourging rod in the fire? Read <hi>Ier.</hi> 50. <hi>v.</hi> 17. to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Since the Saints are ſo beloved of Chriſt the head,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> ought not the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to love one another? If we did, we would not<note n="*" place="margin">Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the Seventy from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing overmuch, though their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory was over Satan immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately. <hi>Luc.</hi> 10.20. <hi>God forbid,</hi> ſays <hi>Paul,</hi> Gal. 6.14. <hi>that I ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce,</hi> i. e. chiefly or immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, <hi>but in the creſs of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </note> rejoyce at one anothers ruine; but as Iſrael, mourne for the loſſe of our brother <hi>Benjamin,</hi> Judg. 21.2, 3. ſaying, Lord, why is it come to paſſe, that one Tribe (and more) is loſt this day in Iſrael? — <hi>If we loved</hi> would we not relieve the poor diſtreſſed bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren? Can we truly ſay we are Chriſts, and our purſes our own? Are not all our goods put into our hands as ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards? Muſt we not give an account how imployed? 'Tis ſtrange, having a note under Gods own hand (even his word) to disburſe to the poor ſo much, and he would allow of it—that we refuſe.— If we ſhould chance lodge our brother a night, 'twere rare. — But as the Jewes formerly ſaid, The firſt day, a man was <hi>Oreach,</hi> a gueſt,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:169877:57"/>the ſecond <hi>Toreach,</hi> a burden; the third,<note place="margin">heaven and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (not earthly things) are the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Saints re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycings.</note> 
               <hi>Barach</hi> a runnagate. So we, fiſh and gueſſe in three dayes ſtink. In the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive time all things were common, ſome ſold their houſes for the common good — The <hi>Macedonians</hi> are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by the apoſtle for giving them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Chriſt, and theirs to ſaints, as need required, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. we muſt not (as ſome do now a dayes) ſay, all thine is mine and mine my own: but all mine is thine, and thine thy own.</p>
            <p>If we loved, we would not ſo eaſily jar; let us ſee the danger of it, and the profit of love: <hi>Scylurus</hi> his will is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, a bundle of Arrows to his ſons; while the Arrows faſt together in a bundle, none eaſily broken; while his ſons knit together in brotherly love, all ſafe; but, <hi>dum ſinguli pugnant, vincun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur omnes.</hi> Twas <hi>Cyrus</hi> policy in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Babylon;</hi> the great rivers running thorow the city, hindered its taking; therefore he cut it out into channels, and then it was even fordable and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable: if love were among us, ſoon would peace, and then we ſhould ſee how <hi>concordiâ parva creſcerent, ut ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gna jam dilabuntur,</hi> ſmall things would increaſe as now great things grow
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:169877:58"/>ſmall.<note place="margin">de Clem. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ceſars</hi> ſafety (ſayes <hi>Seneca</hi>) was the <hi>Romans— Peace—ille ut vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum per quod reſp. cohaeret, ille ſpiritus vitalis quem tot millia trahunt: nihil ipſa per ſe futura niſi onus et praeda, ſi mens illa imperij ſubtrahatur; dolentem dicere verum quid vetat? rege incolumi mens omnibus una; Amiſſo, rupere fidem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For want of love are wars—<hi>hint —caedes, venena, urbium clades, et tota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum exitia gentium, et principum ſub civili haſta capita venalia, et ſubjecta tectis faces et ingentia ſpacia regionum hoſtili flamma re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ucentia; aſpice tot nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſſimarum urbium fundimenta vix nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilia, haec ira dejecit. Aſpice ſolitadines per multa millia ſine habitatione diſertas; has ira exhauſil; aſpice tot memoriae pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dito<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> duces, mali exempla fati; alium ira in cubili ſuo confodit. Sen. de ira, lib</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.— hence wars—murders, poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ruining of Cities, Kingdoms, Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; hence that Princes heads are unci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy ſaleable, Crowns and Scepters trampled under foot <hi>(miſcenſtrue me not, Reader, I am tranſlating Seneca)</hi> hence that famous Cities ſcarce known by their ruines; hence Countreys, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, diſpeopled, in a flame. O my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:169877:58"/>bleeding countrey,<note place="margin">note that every a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable, it muſt be <hi>ſecundum Christum</hi>-ſaints do agree in truth— <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.15. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it is conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy— ſo all haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes agree (as <hi>Pilate</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> are made friends) againſt Chriſt, as <hi>Sampſons</hi> foxes turn tail to tail to do hurt. <hi>Miror qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> omnes he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retici inter ſe diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, contra Chriſtum conſentiunt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ireland!</hi> the hiſtorian ſaid, diſcord was <hi>Venenum in civibus Romanis,</hi> poiſon among them. Love by the pſalmiſt is reſembled to Balſam or the precious ointment <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133. which healeth: if love among mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, we would with the milch kine carry our ark, neither turning to the right hand nor left: if the apoſtle rebuked the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> becauſe ſome ſaid I am of <hi>Apollo,</hi> I of <hi>Cephas</hi> or <hi>Peter,</hi> onely magnifying their own miniſter, — and asked is Chriſt divided? would he not if alive, now ask, is Chriſt torn in pieces? ſo many men, ſo many mindes; <hi>quot capita, tot opiniones</hi> (I had almoſt ſaid) <hi>religiones, deus bone in quae tempora reſervaſti nos?</hi> I am ſure there ſhould be one judgement <hi>de jure,</hi> and one practiſe or charity, though <hi>de facto</hi> neither, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 32.39. <hi>I will give them one heart and one way.</hi> In <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32. the multitude was of one heart and one ſoul: where there are differences in opinion, there needs charity—conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all not at the ſame time nor equally enlightened; conſider Chriſts demean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure to his diſciples in this caſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. they beleeved Chriſt ſhould as a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall King reſtore <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he modeſtly
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:169877:59"/>anſwers, It was not for them <hi>to know times and ſeaſons.</hi> — Thus he deales with obſtinate <hi>Thomas; Reach hither thy fingers,</hi> — be not faithleſſe. — Joh. 20.2.</p>
            <p>But what place is this I ſee, like the <hi>Almanacks</hi> Anatomy full of piercings? Is this that <hi>England</hi> the glory of I lands and envy of Continents? Is this that Iſle which ſtrangers came to ſee? A reed ſhaken with the winde, rather ſhattered in peeces Poore <hi>England,</hi> like <hi>Rebecca</hi> with more then twinnes in her wombe, and whoever prevailes ſhe ſmarts. Poor <hi>England,</hi> like a Rock cut and hammered into a Quarry, to dig ſtones to build up her self in a newer faſhion. Poor <hi>England,</hi> like an Oake cleft aſunder with wedges taken out of her own body.</p>
            <p>Where's the friendſhip between fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies! the love of brethren! the ſeamleſſe coat of Chriſt ſpared by the violent Romane ſouldiers! Where's the thought of comming from one <hi>Adam,</hi> and redeemed by one Chriſt? being one in Chriſt? Where's the thought of one Lord.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Eph. 4, 5.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; one Faith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; one Baptiſme, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; one hope of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? <hi>Quis talia fando, temperet à</hi>—
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:169877:59"/>I will ſumme up all with that of the Poet, never more ſeaſonable—
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,<note place="margin">Heſiodus.</note>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>The peacefull Miniſters begin to jarre,</l>
                  <l>And each Mechanick wages warre.</l>
                  <l>There's peace in hell, 'mongst us a ſtrange confuſion:</l>
                  <l>Is this from heaven? in part, ſure, hells deluſion.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But diſputations may beget know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, (though ofttimes ſtrife) as two flints knockt together, do light. Know, diverſities of opinions muſt be too, to manifeſt their faith who are approved, I <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19. The Lord now doth try his people and prove them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13 1. 'Tis partly want of love makes us cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. The Apoſtles, when Chriſt told them, one of them ſhould betray him, began to examine and accuſe themſelves rather then others, every one ſaying, <hi>Is it I?</hi> — Not ſtraight, Sure it is <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Judas,</hi> — Let us (to prevent cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring) look upon our own unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe — <hi>Non videmus id manticae quod in ter go eſt.</hi> — I have read of a people who when they went abroad, did bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:169877:60"/>eyes to ſee other mens faults; but when they came home, would take out their <hi>eyes,</hi> leſt they ſhould ſee their own. Somewhat like the fiſh that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darkens all the neighbouring water with ſome ſpiſſie vapour which it caſts out of its mouth, that it may ſcape un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found out. So, many private Reformers, like the Lapwing cry, <hi>Here 'tis, here 'tis,</hi> to wit, the neſt of other mens faults, but never come neer their own.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tecum habita, &amp; nôris quam ſit tibi curta ſupellex.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Examine thou thy ſelf, and thou ſhalt find</l>
               <l>Thy ſelf but miſerable, naked, poor &amp; blind, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.17.</l>
            </q>
            <p>They are fitteſt to reprove others, who are moſt free from blame. Otherwiſe men will certainly ſay to thee that Proverb, <hi>Phyſitian heale thy ſelf.</hi> Are not they only fit to preach Chriſt, that are in Chriſt? otherwiſe they do but tell a ſtory as it were of the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> which they know not but by hear-ſay. But a man in Chriſt, preaches what by experience in himſelf he knowes. How can others <hi>promiſe liberty,</hi> who are <hi>themſelves the ſervants of ſinne?</hi> 2 Pet. 2.19. Yet if the Phariſees, ſitting in<note n="*" place="margin">If the right and allowed-of Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor ſpeak, though a wicked man, heare the embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> chaire, bid me do this or that
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:169877:60"/>(if good) I'le do it — If the water be good, whether the pipe be lead or ſilver, it ſhall be all one, I le drink it. Some preach Chriſt <hi>out of envy,</hi> — yet ſince Chriſt is preached, the Apoſtle does rejoyce.</p>
            <p>If we loved,<note place="margin">* Note. <hi>Alencis</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, that Chriſt gave <hi>Judas</hi> the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (though the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not generally received) becauſe he would uſe all the meanes of ſalvation to win him</note> we would pray for one another. 'Tis a ſinne for a Miniſter to forbeare. See 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.23. <hi>God forbid,</hi> ſayes <hi>Samuel, that I ſhould ſinne againſt God in ceaſing to pray for you.</hi> — Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times God forbids to pray, as <hi>Ier.</hi> 14.11. &amp; <hi>Ioh</hi> 1. &amp; <hi>cap</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 16. to ſhew, <hi>quod aegrè poſſit remitti, non impoſſibilitatem;</hi> to ſhew the difficulty to prevaile with God to pardon ſuch great ſinnes and ſinners, not the impoſſibility. Iſrael ſinned againſt God; <hi>Moſes</hi> privately prayes, and the power of faith was ſuch, that Gods hands ſeem tyed. <hi>Let me alone,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>Deut.</hi> 9.14. <hi>Elias</hi> was ſo powerfull, that one calls him <hi>Fraenum coeli,</hi> the bridle of heaven. I know it handle as a Schoole point, that if a Miniſter knew one of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be damn'd, yet he ought to pray for him; for God elſe might uſe the Miniſters negligence in omitting the means, as the means (ſecondarily) of his damnation. 'Tis moſt plain, <hi>Ezek.</hi>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:169877:61"/>3.18. Remember if by uſing lawfull means,<note place="margin">Prius Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes dam. nati quam nati.</note> as prayer — a ſinner be convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed—God is glorified having a new ſon; Chriſt rejoyceth to ſee the work of redemption go forward, the holy Ghoſt has a new temple, the Angels a new charge, the Church comforted and ſtrengthened by the prayers of the new convert; therefore pray— <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Ile fal upon ſome more particular uſes.</p>
            <p>Chriſts beloved are intituled to the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> creatures through him, which are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance uſurped by the wicked;<note place="margin">The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked have the good things of this world (the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no part in the world to come.) <hi>de facto,</hi> but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance as Tyrants and Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, <hi>de jure.</hi>
               </note> all are your—1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. ye being mine.</p>
            <p>Chriſts are never wholly dead in ſin; they may be a ſleep as <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> but <hi>Nathan</hi> awakes the one, the Cock the other; a man dead in ſin is like <hi>Lazarus</hi> in his grave, needs a Chriſt, the reſurrection and the life, to quicken him: the Church in the Canticles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes the truth hereof, <hi>I ſleep, but my heart waketh,</hi> 5.2. A man aſleep in ſin by the preaching of the word may be awakened, his heart (even in his ſin) being towards his God, as <hi>Aſas</hi> 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 15.17. though the high places not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved —Why's this thrown into the kings diſh, if they had not a great ſtroke in matters of religion? Dr. <hi>Andrews.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:169877:61"/>
            <p>The effect of Chriſts love is true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: not to hang down the head <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> like a bullruſh for a day, to whine with Saul for an hour, and after ask counſell of a witch; to mourn and humble ones ſelf with Ahab for a while, and return like the dog to the vomit; to be zealous with <hi>Jehu</hi> for a ſpace (as a reformer) and to worſhip the calves at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel;</hi> to be intentive as <hi>Herod</hi> to <hi>John,</hi> —and after give away his head; to tremble as <hi>Felix momento turbenis,</hi> to turn beleever becauſe others did, as <hi>Magus,</hi> and then offer money to buy the Spirit, is nothing worth; do not the Heathen, the Scribes and Phariſees do more? yet your righteouſneſſe muſt exceed—the wicked may have grace (but not ſanctified) and ſeem for a time more eager then the righteous: he that has ſome fits of an ague (though naturally cold) is hotter for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent then one naturally hot: perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance to the end is the bleſſing of Chriſt, not as <hi>Iudas, Magus, Demas.</hi> —Chriſt gives his grace to repent of every ſin; the ſmalleſt chink in a ſhip may endanger it, repent of thy boſome ſinne; thy <hi>Dalilah, Herodias</hi>—God will be <hi>Alexander</hi> or <hi>Nemo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:169877:62"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Chriſt ſends afflictions out of love: the wounded party, though he know the ſharpneſſe of the Chyrurgions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument and ſmarting ſalves to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, yet ſeeks to be dreſt and launced; ſince Chriſts afflicting hand is for good, be patient — by ſin men forfeit all, life and goods — the wages of ſin, Death —God is mercifull and loving, ſparing the life, and ſequeſtering onely the outward eſtate: is not the life more then raiment? he that gave the life, will with it give all things neceſſary, yea though his people were in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.14. <hi>He can provide a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the wilderneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt's alſo ſuffer, to be conformable to him their head, who was <hi>vir dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> a man of ſorrow.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Thou haſt had many temporall &amp; ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall bleſſings; imploy them to Chriſts honour, hide them not in a napkin, leſt thou be brought to account: To whom much is given, of them much is required.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Where Chriſt loves, he begets ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what like himſelf: <hi>Amor ſemper habet quid ſui ſimile</hi>—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> Has every member and every beloved of Chriſt grace as he?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> According to order they have;
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:169877:62"/>yet thouſands of children ſaved, in whom grace not ſo apparent as in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. 2 Suppoſe the thief on the croſſe had died without confeſſion, yet elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and <hi>(gravidus erat operibus)</hi> great with good works, was ſafe. 3 Divers may be juſtified, and therefore elected and ſaved, yet die before viſible appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of faith; <hi>ſed haec obiter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then hate ſin, O beloved; it ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> any; leaſt a Saint: Chriſt takes ſin at their hands, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> wounds from him of whom he meritted better uſage with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Sin is the ſword that put our Saviour to death; hate that ſword that ſlew thy deareſt friend; conſider ſins odiouſneſſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the vomit of a dog, the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruous cloth, the mire of the ſtreet in which the ſow wallows: do not live as Heathen under the name of Chriſtians, <hi>Muta nomen, vel age fortius.</hi> Let not Chriſt be wounded in the houſe of his friends: never more pretences for Chriſt then now; if the wine good, what need ſo great a buſh? <hi>cur pudeat nos dicere, quod non pudeat hos facere?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Jewel.</hi>
               </note> Contemn the world: <hi>ſine mundum va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere ut vult,</hi> ſayes <hi>Luther,</hi> thou art not of the world. Say to it as <hi>Diogenes</hi> to
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:169877:63"/>his ſervant <hi>Manes</hi> (in <hi>Seneca</hi>) which run away from him (as the world will ſerve thee in time of trouble) <hi>turpe eſſet Manen poſſe vivere ſine Diogene, Diogenem non poſſe vivere ſine Mane:</hi> If thou canſt live without me, Iſe ſtrive to live without (ſerving) thee: think not of husks being converted, think of thy joy and ſpirituall food of comfort; — ſince thy coming home by repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, ſay as the Father, I have wanted my ſweets too long already: remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how the Father fetcht thee home being a great way off in ſin; he went not ſoftly but ran, not a ſtep or two, but quite to meet, did not barely bid wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, but fell upon his neck and kiſſed him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Run not then back to ſin, do not <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texere telam,</hi> but remember Lots wife: ſhe became a pillar of ſalt, which <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> ſayes he ſaw, being after Chriſts death: why into a pillar of ſalt? <hi>ut te ſale condiat,</hi> to ſeaſon thee—</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Hate ſin, thou Gentile and a belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: Chriſt died for thee; the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription was in <hi>Hebrew</hi> for the <hi>Iews,</hi> in <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> (the language of the <hi>Gentiles</hi>) for thee?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Thou O man which continueſt in ſin,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:169877:63"/>what good is it to thee to hear of Chriſts love which reacheth thee not? to hear of water in a well and haſt not a veſſell to draw? even faith; or to hear of Abraham, Iſaac aad Jacobs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in heaven, and thou ſhut out? pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume not on mercy, love, or peace; what haſt thou to do with them as long as thy rebellion againſt God (which is witchcraft) and thy ſins are ſo many?</p>
            <p>Know, as one thief was ſaved to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> teach (us) not to deſpair—ſo another was damned, to teach thee, not to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume. <hi>Exemplum latronis ſervati eſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirandum, non imitandum: Mane</hi> is the devils verb, he bids tarry, time enough to repent; but <hi>Manè</hi> is Gods adverb, he bids repent—early, in the morning of thy youth: The ancient warriers would not accept an old man into their Army, as unfit for ſervice; when thou knoweſt not what elſe to do with thy time and ſelf, art ſure of his entertainment? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he accepted one at the eleventh hour (anſwerable neer to ſix a clock at night, with us) a time to diſcharge ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants (ſayes Mr. <hi>Goodwin</hi> in his <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi>) rather then to hire new: are ſure of thy repentance and accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance at laſt? Chriſt loved us, and gave
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:169877:64"/>himſelf for us when in the prime of age (being ſuppoſed to be about 33.) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves he thy worſt? verifie not that of <hi>Pamphilius, Cum nemini obtrudi poteſt itur ad me.</hi> God called for the firſt of all things in the Law, to teach thee to give him thy heart, <hi>primum vivens,</hi> thy youth and ſtrength; he gave thee all, give not him the worſt, even thoſe—dayes wherein thou haſt no pleaſure, when occaſion of ſinning doth leave thee, not thou ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> If thou loveſt Chriſt, thou wilt not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily hear his Name blaſphemed; a good ſon or ſervant will not hear his father or maſter abuſed: <hi>Do not I hate them that hate thee?</hi> ſayes the Pſalmiſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> If thou continueſt in his love, ſee thy happineſſe hereafter: thou ſhalt ſee Chriſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, face to face: or as the apoſtle, ſee him as he is, that is, not darkly—as in a glaſſe, now, but more plainly, &amp; without reflecting upon the Creatures in which he is now, ſeen—Chriſts humane nature ſhall be ſeen moſt glorious; but no created na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can behold God in full glory, or is capable to comprehend his eſſence per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, but ſhal comprehend him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent &amp; ſatisfaction, though ſome more,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:169877:64"/>ſome leſſe as buckets caſt into the ſea, all are full, yet ſome have more water, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers leſſe, as the capacity of the veſſell is: what manner of love is this? that Chriſt ſhould die, juſtifie—giving faith to lay hold on him and eternall life?</p>
            <q>—et opera illius noſtra ſunt.</q>
            <p>Chriſt has left a letter for us behind <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> him, in which we may ſee his love to us, our duty to him; keep this letter ſafe; God has moſt ſtrangely kept it from ages for thee; ſlight it not, nor ſo great Salvation as is in it offered; it is rich enough in it ſelf without humane liter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature, yet as a handmaid; uſe it to Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity the queen of knowledge; ſlight not a pearl though in a dunghill; <hi>vero nil ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius; Paul</hi> himſelf has quoted a Poet; yet ſure here is knowledge enough; ſearch not too deep into the earth for hidden treaſure, leſt a damp endanger thee, and it — Here in Scripture is <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia,</hi> without which all knowledge is but <hi>inopia</hi>—which can guide our feet into the way of peace; <note n="*" place="margin">Noneſt attenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum quid alij ante nos ſece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint, ſed quid chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus, qui ante omnes eſt, facien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceperit. Cyprian.</note> then follow Chriſt ſpeaking in the word; ſeek to gain the Apoſtles ſpirit to underſtand the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles writings; as for Commentaries and Miniſters, do not <hi>jurare in verba mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri;</hi>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:169877:65"/>follow them as they follow Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>amicus Plato; amicus Ariſtotelis, ſed magis amica veritas,</hi> follow none in an errour—<hi>Siquid legem ſibi dixcrit, nihil contra Zenonis Chryſippive dictum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittere, et unius ſequi ſententiam, non id vitae ſed factionis eſt,</hi> ſayes <hi>Seneca.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gods word is plain—a light, a lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn, God out of love &amp; Juſtice would not leave his word over dark or diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, ſince to guide his people; he has moreover left us an able Commentary, his Spirit. <hi>Vas vitreum ut lambimus, ſicet pultim attingimus.</hi> Take heed of imbracing new Cannons, orders for worſhip—if they be Scripture (which is full) uſe Scripture; if not, if an Angel from heaven bring them, let him be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed.</p>
            <p>Plow up, O Lord, the furrows of our hearts by ſorrow and contrition for ſin, ſowe in the incorruptible ſeed of thy word, water it with the dew of heaven, thy grace from above; make it bring forth fruit in ſome ſixty, in ſome thirty, in all ſome, and in ſome all, to the praiſe of thy Name, the good of our own ſouls, the edifying of our brethren, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. Amen.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:169877:65"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Phoſphore redde diem; quid gandia no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra moraris,</l>
                  <l>Caeſare venturo? Phoſphore redde diem.</l>
               </q>
Day-ſtar, bring the day, make no delay; Our Caeſar is to come, in his kingdome: ô Saviour bring that day, make no delay.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Even ſo come Lord Jeſu, come quickly.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:169877:66"/>
            <head>To the Reverend, His carefully-loving Father, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. RANDOL HOLLAND A Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>IRELAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MY Letters ſeldome arrive ſafely with you in <hi>Ireland,</hi> by reaſon of the diſtance. Wherefore <hi>I</hi> have annext this printed to my Book, which I doubt not but in time (if alive) you'll receive. It will certifie you (ſomewhat) the ſtate of my ſoule (though not of my body.) If you ask me the reaſon of my publiſhing ſo mean an Exerciſe in a time of ſuch Paper-proſtitution: among many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Ile give you (Sir) this, as moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning your ſelf. The death of my ever gallant <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle Captain <hi>Stephen Huſſey,</hi> and the never enough by me deplored loſſe of my two deare Brothers, <hi>Henry</hi> and <hi>Joſhuah Holland,</hi> ſlain in theſe unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall warres, made me firſt apply my ſelf
<pb facs="tcp:169877:66"/>to this ſubject. <hi>I</hi> have comforted my ſelf, conſidering the graces God formerly wrought in them as footſteps of himſelf, and then conſidering his loving to the end; conſidering that afflictions are ſignes of love; that death is beneficiall; and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain death no argument of his hatred: <hi>Joſiah's</hi> death was ſuch. And indeed, <hi>I</hi> had ſcarce with ſighs dryed the teares off my face (which I had ſhed for them) when God bleſt me with a ſon. <hi>I</hi> thought God had ſent me a ſummers day in the winter of my ſorrow; little did I dream its ſun would ſet ſo ſodainly <hi>I</hi> baptized it with your name, and thought with <hi>Hannah</hi> to have given it to the Lord all his dayes. But indeed it proved but an <hi>April</hi> ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine, which had a preſent ſhower waiting on it. God ſaw me not humble enough nor fitted for ſuch a bleſſing. For by that time it had twelve moneths bleſt me with many a ſmile—peor babe! as if it had performed the errand God ſent it for, it returned to him that gave it: doubtleſſe it hath took poſſeſſion of the heaven of Saints for me, of which our Saviour long ſince took poſſeſſion for us all. This made me more earneſtly ſtudy on this ſubject, <hi>(Gods love in affliction)</hi> that I might the more willingly kiſſe the rod that
<pb facs="tcp:169877:67"/>ſcourged me. This was one reaſon made me publiſh theſe lines; That whiles <hi>I</hi> could not enjoy my friends here, (nor my ſweet <hi>Randol</hi>) <hi>I</hi> might at leaſt have, as it were, their Funerall ſermon to read.</p>
            <p>Thus thanking you for your care to wards me in my Education, for your Prayers (of which <hi>I</hi> believe <hi>I</hi> have had benefit) deſiring the continuance of them and your health,—I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your dutiful ſonne,</hi> Hezek. Holland.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Sutton-Valence,</hi> 
                  <date>July <hi>10. 1649.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
